<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fathers vindicated, or, Animadversions on a late Socinian book entitul'd The judgment of the Fathers touching the Trinity, against Doctor Bull's Defence of the Nicene faith by a presbyter of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Deacon, J., Presbyter of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 74 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37295</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13106358</idno>
  <idno type="VID">97513</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240861246</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8462</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13106358</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37295)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 413:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fathers vindicated, or, Animadversions on a late Socinian book entitul'd The judgment of the Fathers touching the Trinity, against Doctor Bull's Defence of the Nicene faith by a presbyter of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Deacon, J., Presbyter of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 134 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ri. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Deacon. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Smalbroke, Thomas. --  Judgment of the fathers concerning the doctrine of the Trinity.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Bull, George, 1634-1710. --  Defensio fidei Nicaenae.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Socinianism.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97513:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97513:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Fathers Vindicated:</hi> OR, ANIMADVERSIONS On a late Socinian Book Entitul'd, <hi>The Judgment of the Fathers Touching the</hi> TRINITY, <hi>against Doctor</hi> Bull<hi>'s Defence of the</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY A Presbyter of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ri. Chiswell,</hi> at the <hi>Rose</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church-Yard,</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:97513:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97513:2"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Fathers Vindicated,</hi> Touching the TRINITY.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:97513:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97513:3"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. A <hi>Character of</hi> M. N. <hi>and of the Scheme that he hath form'd of the Newness of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of the Trinity, and of the Divinity of Jesus Christ.</hi> Page 1.</item>
               <item>CHAP. II. <hi>A General Enquiry in</hi> M. N<hi>'s Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stem.</hi> p. 8.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:97513:4"/>
               <item> CHAP. III. <hi>A Review of the Witnesses which</hi> M. N. <hi>brings in general for the Opinions of the</hi> Unitarians <hi>before the first Council of</hi> Nice. p. 22.</item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. <hi>That neither the Authors of the</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Creed, <hi>nor</hi> Clemens Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus, <hi>were of the Opinions of the</hi> Unitarians. p. 41.</item>
               <item>CHAP. V. <hi>That the</hi> Nazarens, <hi>the</hi> Ebionites, <hi>the</hi> Minaeans, <hi>and the</hi> Alogians, <hi>were justly looked upon as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi> p. 64.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:97513:4"/>
               <item> CHAP. VI. <hi>That neither</hi> Hegesippus, <hi>nor the Fifteen first Bishops of</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>were of the Opinion of the</hi> Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, <hi>or the</hi> Ebionites: <hi>And that the</hi> Alogi <hi>were Hereticks as well as the</hi> Cerinthians. p. 77.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. <hi>That</hi> Justin Martyr <hi>was no Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator.</hi> p. 93.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VIII. <hi>That the Notion of the</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>did not come from the</hi> Platonicks, <hi>but was the antient Notion of the Synagogue, and of the Apostles of our Saviour.</hi> p. 110.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:97513:5"/>
               <item> CHAP. III. <hi>A Review of the Witnesses which</hi> M. N. <hi>brings in general for the Opinions of the</hi> Unitarians <hi>before the first Council of</hi> Nice. p. 22.</item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. <hi>That neither the Authors of the</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Creed, <hi>nor</hi> Clemens Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus, <hi>were of the Opinions of the</hi> Unitarians. p. 41.</item>
               <item>CHAP. V. <hi>That the</hi> Nazarens, <hi>the</hi> Ebionites, <hi>the</hi> Minaeans, <hi>and the</hi> Alogians, <hi>were justly looked upon as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi> p. 64.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:97513:5"/>
               <item> CHAP. VI. <hi>That neither</hi> Hegesippus, <hi>nor the Fifteen first Bishops of</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>were of the Opinion of the</hi> Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, <hi>or the</hi> Ebionites: <hi>And that the</hi> Alogi <hi>were Hereticks as well as the</hi> Cerinthians. p. 77.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. <hi>That</hi> Justin Martyr <hi>was no Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator.</hi> p. 93.</item>
               <item>CHAP. VIII. <hi>That the Notion of the</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>did not come from the</hi> Platonicks, <hi>but was the antient Notion of the Synagogue, and of the Apostles of our Saviour.</hi> p. 110.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:97513:6"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>PAge 12. line 24. <hi>lege</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>P. 24. l. 16. <hi>l. Theodotus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 41. l. 16. <hi>l. Hermas Pastor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 42. l. 18. <hi>l. Century.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 59. l. 19. <hi>l. nunquam eum</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 68. l. 7. <hi>l. Christians that</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 99. l. 10. <hi>l. Catalogue</hi>
               </item>
               <item>l. 16. <hi>l. Elentherus</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 107. l. 12. <hi>l.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97513:6"/>
            <head>THE FATHERS VINDICATED Touching the TRINITY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>A Character of</hi> M. N. <hi>and of the Scheme that he hath form'd of the Newness of the Opinions of the Trinity, and of the Divinity of Jesus Christ.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THO' I have a great regard to the Commands that you lay upon me, yet it is not without some Unwillingness that I have undertaken to examine the Book entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Judgment of the Fathers concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97513:7"/>the Trinity, against Dr.</hi> Bull: For the Reverend and Learned Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> is best able to do this himself, and can do it with very great ease: and his Adversary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Man who seems to have in him a great confidence of Temper, joyn'd to as great Affectation of Novelty; I have little Inclination to be concern'd with him. However, I have learn'd to obey; especially where my Obedience may be thought to do service to Truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> is of the Opinion of <hi>Francis Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> who deny'd the Lawfulness of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking <hi>JESƲS CHRIST,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tom II. <hi>Soc.</hi> p. 710. &amp; 711.</note> and was for that reason detested by <hi>Socinus,</hi> as a Heretick, that renounced the Principles of Christianity, and had a design to bring in among Christians the Jewish Ideas about the Person of the <hi>Messiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socinus</hi> was a zealous Assertor of the Authority of the Holy Scriptures, and proved it with such Arguments, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be answer'd: Especially for the Books of the <hi>New Testament;</hi> he hath shew'd with great Judgment that they can't be suspected of having been corrupted by any Party or Sect among Christians.
<note place="margin">De Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Scr. <hi>C.</hi> 1. §. 3.</note> And where any Text makes evidently against his opinion, yet nothing could provoke him to question the Authority
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97513:7"/>of it. Whosoever is conversant in his Writings, can't but see what infinite pains he hath taken to evade the force of divers of those Texts which prove the Godhead of our Saviour. But <hi>M. N.</hi> little considering the pains that <hi>Socinus</hi> hath taken, and without giving himself any trouble to confute <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to prove the Purity of the Books of the <hi>New Testament;</hi> boldly asserts, that the Gospels and Epistles have been falsified by those whom he calls <hi>Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians;</hi> who, as he tells us, have added to them what they pleas'd.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 30, 31. &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 63. <hi>col.</hi> 1.</note> This Accusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he often repeats with a groundless assurance.</p>
               <p>So that now the state of the Dispute is wholly changed from what it was with <hi>Socinus,</hi> and the Learned Writers of his Sect. It seems we must no longer contend for the Divinity of our Saviour, or the Doctrine of the Trinity: But our Controversy now with <hi>M. N.</hi> and his Collegues, is principally about the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Holy Scripture, just the same that we have with some of the <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> who accuse the Christians of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving corrupted the Gospels. And though at this distance from <hi>Turky,</hi> God be thanked, we are in no danger of that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97513:8"/>Sect, yet we are not so secure against the <hi>Deists</hi> and <hi>Atheists,</hi> who are chiefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in this Controversie, as being the profest Enemies of the Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. The <hi>Socinians</hi> do profess them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves <hi>Christians;</hi> but yet one can hardly think them in earnest that write at this rate. They are either downright <hi>Deists,</hi> or they are certainly in a great forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness towards it; of which they were warn'd long since by <hi>Socinus</hi> himself.
<note place="margin">Tom. I. <hi>p.</hi> 327. Tom. II. <hi>p.</hi> 773. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> He warn'd those of his Sect that deny'd the Worship of <hi>Christ,</hi> as our <hi>M. N.</hi> expresly doth; that if they went on, they would become <hi>Deists</hi> and <hi>Epicureans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, you desire me to let you know my Thoughts of this Book of <hi>M. N.</hi> and to examine the <hi>Plan</hi> which he hath form'd of the Belief of the most Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Antiquity, concerning the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Divinity of our Saviour; which at your desire I will endeavour to do.</p>
               <p>If we may believe <hi>M. N.</hi> he brings us up to the very beginning of the change; and doth all he can to perswade the World, that he sets forth the Manner of it; so that for the future there will be nothing more easie than to judge of the Truth and Apostolical Antiquity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97513:8"/>of the Doctrine of the <hi>Ʋnitarians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But see in a few words what <hi>M. N.</hi> teacheth us of the Antient Faith: He telleth us the Holy Scripture faith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, either of the Trinity, or of the Godhead of our Saviour. So that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scripture, there is but one Person, as well as one Nature in God: and, That <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> is but a meer Man, miraculously born of the Virgin by the virtue of the Holy Ghost; indued with a power of doing Miracles, and at last taken up into Glory to govern the Church, and the World, at least, as far as the Church is concern'd in it.</p>
               <p>He tells us the Apostles writ that Creed which is commonly called by their name; and that they deliver'd no more than that Creed in the confession of Faith which they prescribed to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</p>
               <p>He would have us believe that the first Bishops of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and the first Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of the greatest Cities in the World, who were Successors to the Apostles, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her'd to this belief without any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, till the slaughter and dispersion of the Jews under <hi>Hadrian,</hi> that is till about the year of our Lord 135.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97513:9"/>
               <p> The <hi>Jews</hi> that were converted by the Apostles and their successors, and the <hi>Heathens</hi> that were converted by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, and by Apostolical Men out of <hi>Palestine,</hi> continu'd till then, as he tells us, in the opinion of the present <hi>Ʋnitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About that time, or at least about the year 150, when all the Protestants, as <hi>M. N.</hi> tells us,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 15. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </note> agree that the Doctrine of the Church began to be corrupted, <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> thought fit to set up the Doctrine of the Trinity. He averr'd that <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> was the Eternal Word: He proved it against <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew, by the Apparitions of God that are related in the Old Testament.</p>
               <p>He tells us that as soon as <hi>Justin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> had published his Conference with <hi>Trypho,</hi> a great number of Christians quitted the simple Notions that they had of the Deity, to perplex themselves with those new Ideas of the Trinity. That they then took up the Doctrine of the Godhead of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> which was an Opinion never before heard of. This Belief spread abroad, and took so gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, from <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s time to the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> that although the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Christians, whom he calls the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarens,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97513:9"/>the <hi>Mineans,</hi> the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> the <hi>Cerinthians,</hi> and the <hi>Alogians,</hi> defended the ancient Doctrine concerning the Unity of God, and rejected the Belief of the Trinity; and of the Godhead of the Saviour, properly so call'd; yet the multitude of those that believ'd the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the eternal Godhead of Jesus Christ, prevail'd in the first Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> and made this Heresie pass into an Article of Faith.</p>
               <p>This, Sir, is the System of <hi>M.N.</hi> which he establishes by divers conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations out of Antiquity, and which he makes as probable as he can, by answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dr. <hi>Bull's</hi> Arguments, with all the dexterity and confidence that he is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of.</p>
               <p>I desire you would not expect that I should dispute with <hi>M. N.</hi> about all that he alledges, and particularly about that which he saith against Dr. <hi>Bull.</hi> The Doctor, who will probably wait for all the Three parts of <hi>M. N</hi>'s Book, of which he hath yet publisht, but the first, will be very well able to do right both to himself and his cause.</p>
               <p>Nor will I take notice of all that he saith, without authority, and yet with as much confidence as if he had all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97513:10"/>in himself. It is enough to let the <hi>Ʋnitarians</hi> see how rash their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion is in his Assertions, to abate some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Veneration which they have for an Author of so little Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Modesty.</p>
               <p>To do this with the more clearness and usefulness; I think it the best way.</p>
               <p>First, <hi>To examine his System in General.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>To inquire into the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that he brings to justifie it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Thirdly, <hi>To make it appear, that he hath no ground to accuse</hi> Justin Martyr, <hi>as he doth, of Innovation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I think I may under these three Heads take in all that is worth considering in his <hi>Judgment of the Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>A General Enquiry into</hi> M. N<hi>'s System.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE shall first give a general Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Opinion, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctrine of the Trinity, and the Godhead of our Saviour.</p>
               <p n="1">I. He saith, That the writings of the Old Testament have nothing in them to ground the Belief of a Trinity, and of the Godhead of the <hi>Messiah.</hi> He
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97513:10"/>saith <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> is the first that hath gather'd both the one and the other out of the Writings of the Old Testament. Herein <hi>M.N.</hi> agreeth with the present <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to say nothing of what <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> and his Apostles have taught of this Matter, about which he makes a great stir to little purpose; it's plain, that the first <hi>Christians</hi> are against him in the Disputes that they had with the <hi>Jews</hi> before <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> had written. And this it will be no hard Matter to prove.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is scarce to be conceiv'd; that <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> having a <hi>Jew</hi> to dispute with, should go about to convert him with a new Notion of which himself was the first Author; and not only so, but that he should have the confidence to publish in the face of the World a private Dispute, which he had with a <hi>Jew</hi> upon that subject.</p>
               <p>We may well imagine, that a <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> who rejects the Trinity and the Godhead of our Saviour, would easily agree with a <hi>Jew</hi> about these Opinions, and leave them out of the dispute, to make the <hi>Christian</hi> Religion more easie and agreeable to a <hi>Jew.</hi> But supposing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97513:11"/>that before <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> these Doctrines had never been heard of, and that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin</hi> thought he had discover'd them in the Writings of the Old Testament, is it probable, that he would have made them such principal Points of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie in disputing with a <hi>Jew,</hi> And that he would have pretended to ground them upon Authorities out of the Old Testament?</p>
               <p n="2">2. We need but consider the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how <hi>Justin</hi> disputes with the <hi>Jew</hi> to be satisfi'd, That he did not advance any new Doctrine.</p>
               <p>He proposeth two Questions. The First, Whether <hi>Jesus</hi> is the promised <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssias?</hi> Which he saith he can maintain against <hi>Trypho,</hi> though he should not acknowledge <hi>Jesus</hi> to be any more than meer Man. The Second, Whether <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ</hi> had a Being before his Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation? Whether he was God? Whether he was born of a Virgin? Which he affirms to have been the Doctrine of the Prophets, and of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> himself. <hi>Justin</hi> advanceth these Propositions, as being such as were generally receiv'd among the <hi>Christians.</hi> He quotes his Authorities out of the Books of the Old Testament; and carefully confutes the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97513:11"/>different Solutions which the <hi>Rabbins</hi> used to evade these Arguments: Which sheweth, that his Proofs were drawn out of Scripture, and were not new to the <hi>Jews;</hi> but that the Dispute having continu'd ever since the Apostles times, the <hi>Jews</hi> had been diligent in finding Answers to these Objections; and that, as it often happens among them that plead for a bad Cause, they were already divided among themselves; such an Answer as hit the Fancy of one <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin,</hi> being not satisfactory to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It will be sufficient to bring one Example of it, out of many that I could produce.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philo</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>De opif. Mundi p.</hi> 16. <hi>c. De confus. ling. p.</hi> 395, &amp; 396. <hi>De profug. p.</hi> 460, &amp; 461. <hi>Et de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. p.</hi> 1048, &amp; 1049. <hi>De epif. Mund. p.</hi> 32.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Et de plant. Noe p.</hi> 217.</p>
                  </note> long before the Year of our Lord 40, in explaining these Words of God, <hi>Let us make Man in our own Image,</hi> makes this Reflection, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>This implyeth the taking in of others as fellow Workmen.</hi> And elsewhere he maintains, that Man was made in the Image or Likeness of the Word. The <hi>Christians</hi> having afterward alledged that Passage for the Proof of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the <hi>Jews</hi> were obliged to say, some of them that God spake to the Angels, others that he spake in the Plural because
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97513:12"/>of his Majesty, and others that he spake to the Elements, out of which the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Man was to be compos'd. These Answers, being invented before <hi>Justin</hi>'s time,
<note place="margin">P. 285. <hi>B. C. D.</hi>
                  </note> he mentions, and rejects them with Scorn. It appears then, That the <hi>Christians</hi> before <hi>Justins</hi> time did believe the Trinity, because the <hi>Jews</hi> in his time were so divided among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves as I have shewn, and made such different Answers to the Objection which was made to them by the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</hi> But I shall shew, that the <hi>Jews</hi> before <hi>Justin</hi>'s time accus'd the <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of acknowledging the <hi>Messias</hi> to be true God, as well as Man. This will plainly appear by what followeth.</p>
               <p>We need but consider in what manner <hi>Justin</hi> speaks of those among the <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that rejected the Divinity of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and believ'd him to be a Man born of <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> for that is what he expresseth in these Terms, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>A Man born of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Parents,</hi> which he opposeth to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>A man born of a Virgin.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 267.</note> See how he expresseth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97513:12"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>For there are some among us who confess that that he is CHRIST, but affirm him to be Man born of humane Parents; with whom I do not agree; nor would it be said by most of them that are of my Opinion; for we have been commanded by CHRIST himself, not to believe the Doctrines of Men, but to believe those things, which were publisht by the Holy Prophets, and taught by CHRIST himself.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as it is here oppos'd to the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hath a great extent in the Greek; it signifies the far greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that here <hi>Justin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> speaks of, he consider'd as such a sort of <hi>Christians</hi> as those whom <hi>Tiberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> would have made, if the Senate would have consented to it, by procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>Apotheosis</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> because of his great Miracles, without examining whether he were born of a Virgin,
<note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog</hi> c. 5.</note> or of <hi>Joseph</hi> and the Virgin. But withal it appears, that <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> together with the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is the Body of the <hi>Christians,</hi> were of the Opinion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97513:13"/>which he defends against <hi>Trypho</hi>'s Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; and that they defended it, as grounded upon the Authorities of the Apostles, and of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> himself.</p>
               <p>Certainly if we give our selves the trouble to examine the Pains that <hi>Rabbi Jochanan</hi> takes to instruct the <hi>Babylonian Jews,</hi> of whom he was the Chief, how to answer the <hi>Christians</hi> who prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the plurality of Persons in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, out of the Books of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament, we shall see that it was not a Doctrine brought up by <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> after <hi>Hadrians</hi>'s time.
<note place="margin">Gemara <hi>in cap.</hi> 4. <hi>lib.</hi> Sanhedrin <hi>fol.</hi> 38. <hi>col.</hi> 2.</note> This <hi>Rabbin</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly answers the Arguments which the <hi>Christians</hi> drew from those words, <hi>Gen.</hi> I. 26. <hi>Let us make Man in our own Image,</hi> together with the like words, <hi>Gen.</hi> XI. 7. <hi>Come, let us go down and confound their Language,</hi> and likewise from <hi>Deut.</hi> IV. 7. from 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> VII. 23. from <hi>Dan.</hi> VII. 9, And he reports a more antient Objection drawn from that which we read of the Angel, that conducted the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> in the <hi>Wilderness. Exod.</hi> XXIII. 21. Can any one that hath not lost his Reason, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that <hi>Rabbi Jochanan,</hi> who liv'd amongst the <hi>Jews</hi> a little after the Year of our Lord 170, and in a Countrey
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97513:13"/>that was almost always at War with the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, should go about to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the Notions of <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> whose name it is not likely he had ever heard of, if these Notions had not been common to all Christians? At least if he had seen that these Notions generally gain'd ground in the Belief of the People, would he not have spared his pains in answering those Arguments, and taken a shorter way to confute this Doctrine, by shewing that it was a new thing which he had seen the very beginning of, and that it was not yet so much as the common Opinion of those that were separated from the Synagogue?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> saith that those Doctrines of the Divinity of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, were not deliver'd in any of the Books of the <hi>New Testament;</hi> but that they have been invented since the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of those Books: And yet the Jews reject these Books on this very account, because they contain these Doctrines; which, say they, are contrary to what hath been deliver'd in the <hi>Old Testament.</hi> It might seem a very strange thing that the Jews should find these Doctrines in the Gospels, and the other Books of the <hi>New Testament;</hi> and that the <hi>Ʋnitarians,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97513:14"/>who call themselves Christians, and therefore ought to be much better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with these Books, should not be able to discover any such thing in them. Or if it be shewn them that these Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are there, in those very places which the Jews object against, that the <hi>Ʋnitarians</hi> should dispute against the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Sense of the words, and endeavour to elude it with forced and far fetch'd Interpretations. But the Strangeness goes off, when we see that these Gentlemen do not believe themselves. We cannot but judg so of this Writer, who, though he disputes and denies as confidently as the rest, yet confesses at last that these Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are in the <hi>New Testament;</hi> for he says they were foisted in there by the <hi>Trinitarians.</hi> And for this, if you will not take his word, you have <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s that said it before him.</p>
               <p>But that the first Disciples of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles did not receive from them the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines either of the Trinity, or of the Godhead of our Saviour; of this he is certain, because they were not known before <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s time.
<note place="margin">Plin. <hi>lib.</hi> X. <hi>Epist.</hi> 97.</note> If so, what could <hi>Pliny</hi> the Younger mean? Who, after he had informed himself of the Worship of the Christians, about the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97513:14"/>year of our Lord 106, gave this account of it to <hi>Trajan,</hi> That the Christians wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped <hi>Christ</hi> as a God; for it was in their publick Worship that,
<note place="margin">Luciani Philopatris</note> he saith they did <hi>carmen Christo quasi Deo dicere, say a Hymn to Christ as God.</hi> What could the Author of the <hi>Philopatris,</hi> that goes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Lucian,</hi> mean by teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Trinity is the God of the Christians?
<note place="margin">V. Bulli <hi>def. Fid.</hi> Nic. <hi>p.</hi> 124, 125.</note> This Author was contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary with <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> and very well knew the Christian Religion, and attributes this Doctrine to St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apostle. What could be the meaning of <hi>Trypho,</hi> who was <hi>Justin</hi>'s Adversary,
<note place="margin">Justin. M. <hi>adv.</hi> Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonem.</note> in objecting it so often to the Christians that they worshipped <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> as a God? What could be the meaning of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losopher <hi>Celsus,</hi> that flourished under <hi>M.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Orig <hi>contra</hi> Cels. <hi>p.</hi> 51, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 162.</note>
                  <hi>Aurelius,</hi> when he reproach'd the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians with believing the Divinity of our Saviour, as a Doctrine that was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally condemned both by the <hi>Jews,</hi> and by the <hi>Gentiles?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though <hi>M. N.</hi> knoweth but little of the Writings of those times, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may be excused for thinking others to be as ignorant as himself in these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; yet he ought not to take all the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97513:15"/>World to be such Fools, that he may pass upon them what he will by his bare Affirmation. But it is plain that he doth so in these following Instances, which have no other bottom but his vain Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations. <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> publish'd his Dialogue about the year of our Lord 140. It is a Dispute with the <hi>Jews</hi> in defence of the Christian Faith. Well, what then? He tells us that <hi>Justin</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanceth a Doctrine before wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of, concerning the Person of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and the Nature of God; namely, that <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> is God, and that he ought to be worshipp'd; that he was begotten of the Father before all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; that there are in the Godhead Three that are different <hi>numero,</hi> though not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. He tells us farther, that as soon as <hi>Justin</hi> had publish'd this Work, which was in Greek, and which was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the greatest part of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, all the World forsook the Ideas which they had before of the Deity, and of the Person of our Saviour; and that they began every where to worship him, whereas they before look'd upon him as a meer Creature. He tells us that hereby they gave a new and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97513:15"/>just Scandal to the Jews, and made the convert Gentiles return to the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try which they had forsaken. He saith, the <hi>Nazarens</hi> and the <hi>Ebionites</hi> opposed themselves to this Innovation; but all in vain; for all the World was so inchanted with this Novelty, that they run into it blindfold. It was fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd and embraced both by Clergy and People throughout all Nations.</p>
               <p>Surely <hi>M. N.</hi> must believe that <hi>Justin M.</hi> had Apostles whom he sent to all parts, and bestow'd on them the gift of Tongues, and of working Miracles; otherwise how could he be able in thirty years to overthrow that Gospel which <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and his Apostles, and their Successors, had been now near an hundred years in establishing? For not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, about the year 170,
<note place="margin">L. I. c. 2, 3, <hi>&amp;</hi> L. III. c. 4.</note>
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi> declares that the common Faith of the Churches all over the World was that of the Trinity, and of the Godhead of our Saviour. The Apostles also of <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> must necessarily have been more powerful than our Saviour's Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles. For according to <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew, and according to <hi>M. N.</hi> the Gospel would have been much more probable,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97513:16"/>if it had not been perplex'd with the Doctrines of the Trinity, and of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of the Messias.</p>
               <p>What is singular in this System of <hi>M. N</hi>'s. is, that according to him the Jews were not sensible of this change, nor did they ever reproach the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans with it; that the Pagans and their Philosophers did not take notice of it, nor ever objected it against the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; that all the Christians throughout the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire receiv'd the change without the least dispute; that those without the bounds of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire receiv'd it without any the least repugnance; in a word, that these Christians, that were so ready to run to Martyrdom for the defence of their Religion, which in the esteem of <hi>M.N.</hi> had been so very reasonable in case there had been nothing in it of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and of the Godhead of <hi>Jesus Christ;</hi> were still more ready to throw away their Lives in defence of a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that was new, and that <hi>M. N.</hi> thinks more extravagant and absurd than any that was ever before heard of in the World.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97513:16"/>
               <p> We learn from an <hi>Anonymous</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,
<note place="margin">Enseb. <hi>Hist. Eccl.</hi> V. 28.</note> that writ in the beginning of the Third Century, that <hi>Artemon</hi> boldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd that which <hi>M. N.</hi> maintains at this time, <hi>viz.</hi> that the first Disciples of the Apostles knew nothing of the Trinity, nor of the Incarnation of the Word; and that the Doctrine which affirms that <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> was a meer Man, was the Doctrine of the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Church, till the time of <hi>Victor</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of <hi>Zephyrin,</hi> that is till about the year of our Lord 190, or 200. <hi>M. N</hi>'s Assertion is a little more within compass. He contents himself with saying that the Doctrine of the <hi>Ʋnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> was the common opinion of the Christian Church till the time of <hi>Justin Martyr.</hi> So that he allows the Doctrine of the Trinity, and of the Godhead of our Saviour, to be fifty years older than <hi>Artemon</hi> did. Another Unitarian Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that may be a little modester than <hi>M. N.</hi> may afterwards happen to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form his account, and so carry up the Original of the Faith that we defend as high as the time of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> or the Apostles; and yet he may oppose it at last as <hi>M. N.</hi> doth, by questioning
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97513:17"/>the Authority or the Purity of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>But after this General Reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>M. N</hi>'s System, which may be suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to overthrow the whole design of his Treatise against Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> we shall enter into a more particular Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what he sets forth, to give some sort of account of the Chymerical Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stem which he hath framed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>A Review of the Witnesses which</hi> M. N. <hi>brings in general for the Opinions of the</hi> Unitarians <hi>before the first Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of</hi> Nice.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> makes no scruple of charging Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> with unfair dealing, for bringing the Authority of but twenty Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, whom he calls Approved Men, to prove the consent of the whole Church to the Doctrine of our Saviour's Divinity before the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> when he can produce two hundred that held the <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians</hi> Doctrine upon this point; and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97513:17"/>thereupon he triumphs over the Doctor for having impos'd upon his Reader, by the liberty which he hath taken to pick out what Authorities he pleas'd, and to reject such as condemned his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>But <hi>M. N.</hi> is grosly mistaken; for Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> hath followed the Method of <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius Lirinensis,</hi> which is approved by all Christians, and by <hi>M. N.</hi> himself: It is this, that a Doctrine is to be accounted Catholick, when it hath the approbation of all, every where, and at all times. That the belief of the Divinity of our Saviour had this Character the Doctor hath proved by above twenty Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, which he hath brought out of several places of them that lived in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ages, before the first <hi>Nicene</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, which Witnesses were look'd upon always as Orthodox in those times. Twenty Authors of this Character are sufficient to establish this truth.</p>
               <p>If Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> hath qualified these twenty Witnesses as approved Fathers, he might very well call them so, both because these Authors have been always look'd upon as true Disciples of the Apostles, and also because the Doctor hath quoted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97513:18"/>only such Books as the Church hath always reputed authentick or worthy of those illustrious Authors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. N</hi>'s two hundred pretended Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, whose works are perished by reason of their Errors, are a Dream of his own; and consequently are of no authority in the least to be thus oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in a heap to the Fathers that are proposed by Dr. <hi>Bull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But who after all are these Witnesses that in those Apostolical times maintain'd the Doctrine of the <hi>Ʋnitarians? M. N.</hi> reckons among his Witnesses: <hi>Theodotion, Symmachus Paulus, Samosatenus, Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> of <hi>Byzantium, Apollonides, Hermophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Lucianus,</hi> the Authors of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical Recognitions and Constitutions: Melito</hi> Bishop of <hi>Sardis,</hi> the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> whom he supposeth to have had great Churches in <hi>Palestine,</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> and in <hi>Arabia,</hi> and the <hi>Mineans</hi> that were spread all over <hi>Asia;</hi> moreover all the Fifteen first Bishops of <hi>Jerusalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this is but a Chimaera of <hi>M. N's,</hi> who Fancies what he pleaseth, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Disputes for it, as if he writ for none but ignorant People.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97513:18"/> 1st. We have Reason to wonder, how <hi>M. N.</hi> came to forget <hi>Artomon,</hi> who is mention'd by the Fathers of the Second Council of <hi>Antioch,</hi> as the first Author that held the Opinions of <hi>Paulus Samo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satonus,</hi> which they condemned about the Year 270; so obscure and unknown were the Names of the rest of them at that time.</p>
               <p n="2">2ly. Why doth he not take Care to oppose to Dr. <hi>Bull's</hi> Witnesses, some Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors that were Succcessors to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, and that lived in the Ages next their Times? For he doth not quote any Writer, but such as lived after <hi>Justin Martyr's</hi> time; and <hi>Melito</hi> the most an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient of his pretended Witnesses present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Apology to <hi>M. Aurelius,</hi> about the Year of our Lord 169, or perhaps some years later.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. How unreasonably doth he couple the <hi>Ʋnitarians,</hi> that thought Jesus Christ to be meer Man, or begotten of <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> or of <hi>Mary</hi> by the operation of the Holy Ghost, to such as <hi>Lucian</hi> Presbyter of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and the Authors of the Recognitions and Constitutions, who own'd the Divinity of Jesus Christ and his Pre-existence, tho' their Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97513:19"/>of the Divinity were very imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and not very agreeable to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures and good Sense? The <hi>Arrians</hi> as <hi>M. N.</hi> tells us, and particularly <hi>Eusebius</hi> of <hi>Caesarea</hi> were the greatest Enemies of the <hi>Ʋnitarians:</hi> Nevertheless he doth them the Favour to reckon them among the <hi>Ʋnitarians,</hi> to oppose them to the Witnesses that are brought by Dr. <hi>Bull.</hi> It is plain that he doth this to abuse ignorant People, who do not examine so closely into Matters. The <hi>Arians</hi> did own the Pre-existence of the Word, and proved it from Texts of both Old and New Testament; and the <hi>Ʋnitarians</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> reject it as a Doctrine that hath no ground in Sacred Books. But for all that <hi>M. N.</hi> takes in those that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the opinion, which was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards defended by <hi>Arius,</hi> among the Disciples of <hi>Artemon</hi> and <hi>Paulus Samosa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus,</hi> as some kind of Officers take in any that come in their way to make a false Muster, not regarding how fit they are for service, for they intend them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a present shew.</p>
               <p>Let us look a little more particularly into the Characters of <hi>M. N</hi>'s Witnesses. The most ancient of them is <hi>Melito</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97513:19"/>of <hi>Sardis,</hi> whom one would not have expected in his Roll, for this <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito</hi> writ a Treatise with this Title, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is as much as to say, <hi>about the Incarnation.</hi> And yet <hi>M.N.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euseb. L. IV. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note> list's him for an <hi>Ʋnitarian</hi> because he writ another piece Intituled, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> infers from this Title, that <hi>Melito</hi> held that Jesus Christ was a Creature; but thereby he only betrays his Ignorance. For it appears by the Title of the Book that <hi>Melito</hi> was so far from designing to prove that Jesus Christ was but a Creature, as <hi>M. N.</hi> falsly imagines, that he writ it to shew that Jesus Christ was not a Creature, but the only Son of God by Generation properly so called. His scope being to solve an Objection which was made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Filiation of the Son, out of that Greek Translation of the VIII. of <hi>Proverbs</hi> in which the Divine Wisdom saith <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>God created me in the beginning of his way;</hi> which Passage <hi>Justin M.</hi> hath consider'd in his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue with <hi>Trypho,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 284.</note> and the other Fathers have explain'd it against the Objections of the <hi>Arians.</hi> That this is no ill grounded conjecture, will appear by the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97513:20"/>Testimony of an Author, that writ in the beginning of the Third Century a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Heresie of <hi>Artemon,</hi> who reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>Melito</hi> among the defenders of our Saviours Divinity.
<note place="margin">Eusch. L. V. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</note>
                  <hi>Nam</hi> Irenaei <hi>quidem, &amp;</hi> Melitonis, <hi>&amp; reliquorum scripta, quis est qui ignoret, in quibus Christum Deum simul &amp; hominem praedicaverunt?</hi>
                  <q>For who is there that doth not know the works of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> and <hi>Melito,</hi> and others, in which they have set forth Christ both as God and Man?</q>
               </p>
               <p>The Second Witness that <hi>M. N.</hi> reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon, is <hi>Theodotion,</hi> who was by some People, as <hi>Jerom</hi> tells us, affirm'd to be an <hi>Ebionite. Epiphanius</hi> saith, that he was a Pagan by Birth, and turn'd Christian. But what fort of Christian? He profest the Opinions of <hi>Tatian,</hi> of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion,</hi> and of <hi>Ebion.</hi> After this he turn'd Jew, renouncing Christianity and receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Circumcision. He learn'd Hebrew, and translated the Old Testament in the time of the Emperor <hi>Severus.</hi> This is <hi>M. N</hi>'s mighty Critick, and his Witness of the highest Authority. I must Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, that some of the Greek Churches had so good an Opinion of <hi>Theodotions</hi> Translation of <hi>Daniel,</hi> that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97513:20"/>it before the Septuagint Version. But how doth this prove that <hi>Theodoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> if he was sometimes an <hi>Ebionite,</hi> was therefore lookt upon as an orthodox Christian, or one to whose Judgment they ought to pay any great deference? Besides, who doth not know that the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches, who had the Septuagint translated into Syriack and Latin, did constantly follow the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gint in the Book of <hi>Daniel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Symmachus</hi> is another of <hi>M. N</hi>'s Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, but he is just such another as <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotion,</hi> that is, only such a one, as a Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that regarded his Credit, would be asham'd to reckon of his side. <hi>Symma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> was by Religion a <hi>Samaritan;</hi> he left the <hi>Samaritans</hi> because they had not a sufficient value for his Merits, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the Jewish Religion; he was disgu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted at the Jews because they also did not preferr him as he thought he deserv'd, and therefore he turn'd Christian; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he went over to the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> and undertook to write for their Opinions. This he did in a Comentary upon S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew's</hi> Gospel, not that which we have, but the <hi>Nazarens</hi> Gospel, which all Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans since have lookt upon as an Apochry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97513:21"/>piece, and a meer Forgery. Hath not <hi>M. N.</hi> great reason to triumph in the Merits of such an Author?</p>
               <p>Now for another of his Witnesses, no less remarkable than the former. He brings in <hi>Theodotus</hi> a Currier, who was born at <hi>Byzantium,</hi> and came afterwards to live at <hi>Rome.</hi> There he was Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by Pope <hi>Victor,</hi> for being the first Teacher of this Heresie in that City. He was the more remarkable, because <hi>Artemon,</hi> or some of his Disciples after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, had the impudence to say, that <hi>Victor</hi> himself was a maintainer of this Heresie, and that before <hi>Victors</hi> being Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Doctrine that asserted Jesus Christ to be meer Man was receiv'd by the Church without any Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. These are the words of that Writer.
<note place="margin">Euseb. V. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</note>
                  <hi>Quomodo eos non pudet hujus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi calumniam adversus</hi> Victorem <hi>concin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare, cum certo sciant</hi> Theodotum <hi>coriari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, qui defectionis illius Deum abnegantis parens &amp; author fuit, primusque Christum nudum hominem esse asseruit, per</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorem <hi>à communione ecclesiae ejectum fuisse. Nam si, ut aiunt,</hi> Victor <hi>eadem sentiebat quae illorum docet impietas, cur</hi> Theodotum <hi>opinionis illius authorem ab ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiâ
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97513:21"/>removit?</hi>
                  <q>How are they not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sham'd, saith he, to throw this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny upon <hi>Victor,</hi> when they very well know that <hi>Theodotus</hi> the Currier, who was the Father and Author of that Apostacy of denying God, and who was the first that asserted Jesus Christ to be meer Man, was cast out of the Communion of the Church by <hi>Victor?</hi> For if, as they say, <hi>Victor</hi> was of the opinion which they impiously hold, why did he excommunicate <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus,</hi> who was the Author of that Opinion?</q>
               </p>
               <p>As for <hi>Apollonides</hi> and <hi>Hermophilus,</hi> who are produced by <hi>M. N.</hi> with such high Characters, he must either be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly void of shame, or he hath never read that part of <hi>Eusebius</hi> which I have now quoted. For see the Character which this <hi>Anonymous</hi> Author in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sebius</hi> gives of them. After having set forth that they despised the simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of the Scriptures, and studied only human Learning and Sciences, making them a rule by which to judge of matters of Faith, He accuseth them of having corrupted the Sacred Books under pretence of Correcting them; he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97513:22"/>offers to convict them of having falsified the Scriptures by comparing the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies that were in their hands, and by shewing the diversity of Readings that was to be found in their own Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies. This Corruption he chargeth particularly on the Copies that were revised by <hi>Theodotus,</hi> and those that were revised by <hi>Asclepiodotus.</hi> He sheweth that <hi>Hermophilus</hi> had also made several Corruptions in the Text, and that <hi>Apollonides</hi> had done the like in a first and second review. And then he makes this reflection upon the bold Impiety of these Men; <hi>Quantae porro audaciae sit ejusmodi facinus, ne ipsos qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ignorare credibile est. Aut enim sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras scripturas à Sancto Spiritu dictatas esse non credunt, ac proinde infideles sunt; aut semetipsos Spiritu Sancto sapientiores esse existimant, ac proinde quid aliud sunt quam Daemoniaci? Neque enim negare possunt hoc facinus à se admissum esse, cum ipsorum manu descripta snt exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaria, neque ab illis à quibus in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianâ side instituti sunt ejusmodi codices acceperint, Nec ostendere possint exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, ex quibus sua illa deseripserunt.</hi>
                  <q>And for such a Crime as this, it is scarce to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97513:22"/>believ'd, that they could be ignorant how horrible a thing it is. For they must either believe, that the Holy Scriptures were not dictated by the Holy Ghost, and then they were Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels; or they must think that they are wiser than the Holy Ghost, and if so, what are they but <hi>Daemoniacks?</hi> Nor can they deny that they are guilty of this Crime, for the Copies are of their own hand writing, and they neither receiv'd such Books from those who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed them in the Christian Faith, nor can they produce the Originals out of which they transcribed them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paulus Somasatenus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Antioch</hi> was a true <hi>Socinian,</hi> for he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd nothing more than human to be in our Lord Jesus Christ. He suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Demetrius</hi> in that See, but soon after his coming in, he was discover'd to be an Impostor that conceal'd He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical Notions. Whereupon they as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled a Council against him at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch.</hi> There at first he avoided Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation by making before the Council, and all the people there as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, a satisfactory Profession of the Catholick Faith, after he had used
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97513:23"/>many vain endeavours to disguise his Opinions. Afterwards he relapsed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Heresie which himself had condemned, and he was so well dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd and convicted of it, that he could not escape being condemned in a very numerous Council, that was assembled upon his account out of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Provinces of the Roman Empire. And in a <hi>Synodical Epistle</hi> yet extant, they acquainted the world what kind of Man he was. Particularly they shew'd how he made the Episcopal Dignity a means to heap up excessive ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; they shew'd, his Ambition, in having joyn'd to his Episcopal Office, the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Dignity of being <hi>Ducenarius,</hi> which render'd him formidable to all the people of <hi>Antioch;</hi> his Vanity, in seeking applause in the Church as if he were on a Theatre; and his Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiousness, in keeping young Wenches in his house, and suffering his Clergy to do the like, and so indulging them in their Lewdness, that he might be himself supported in his. This is the brave Man whom the <hi>Ʋnitarians</hi> so highly exalt.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97513:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Domnus</hi> being set up in <hi>Pauls</hi> room, could not get Possession of the Bishop's house in <hi>Antioch;</hi> that City being then in Possession of <hi>Zenobia</hi> Queen of <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myra,</hi> who was half a Jew, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could not but favour <hi>Paul,</hi> being so near her in Religion. But soon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Emperor <hi>Aurelian</hi> having got Possession of the City, and there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd <hi>Zenobia,</hi> receiv'd Complaints from the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> against <hi>Paul,</hi> who, notwithstanding his depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, kept possession of the Bishop's house, and also from <hi>Paul</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of the Injustice of those that condemned him. <hi>Aurelian</hi> being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to gratifie them that were most capable to do him Service, and not willing to concern himself otherwise in their Affairs, referr'd the considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of these complaints to the Bishops of the Diocesses' of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Millan.</hi> They condemned <hi>Paul</hi> as a Heretick, whereupon he was driven out of the Bishops house by command of the Emperor <hi>Aurelian.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euseb. L. VII. <hi>c.</hi> 27. &amp; se{que}</note> After which we hear no more of him, but that his Sect was continued by one <hi>Lucian</hi> Priest of that City, who was therefore
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97513:24"/>excommunicated by three Bishops of <hi>Antioch</hi> sucessively.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Lucian</hi> our Author will have to be the same with the famous <hi>Lucian</hi> Priest of <hi>Antioch,</hi> who was Martyr'd about sorty years after the outing of <hi>Paulus Samosatenus.</hi> We cannot blame our <hi>Socinians</hi> that they are willing to adorn their Sect with his Name, for did so the <hi>Arrians</hi> before them, being taught so to do by their Master <hi>Arius,</hi> who pretended to be this <hi>Lucian's</hi> Disciple, as appears by his Letter to <hi>Eusebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> whom he calls <hi>Collucianist,</hi> because they both held the Opinions of <hi>Lucian.</hi> But as it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that no Man can be both <hi>Arrian</hi> and <hi>Samosatenian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiphan. Haeres. 69. <hi>p.</hi> 732.</note> for the <hi>Arrians</hi> Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matize the <hi>Samosatenians</hi> as damnable Hereticks, so that <hi>Lucian</hi> the Martyr was of neither of those Sects, it appears by the Creed which is yet extant, and by other Testimonies which the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> hath brought together in the Book that <hi>M. N.</hi> pretends to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Apostolical Recognitions and Constitutions;</hi> these Books do not at all make for <hi>M. N</hi>'s Opinion, because they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97513:24"/>are full of <hi>Arrian</hi> Doctrines, which are not consistent with those of our <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians.</hi> But <hi>M. N.</hi> hath a mind to shew that he is not too scrupulous in his choice of Witnesses. Though he condemns these very Writers of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancy, for believing that they saw sufficient Proofs of the Pre-existence of Jesus Christ as to his Divinity in the Books of the Old and New Testament, but nothing comes amiss to him, he knows how to make use of any thing that comes in his way, whether it makes for him or against him. Which Licentiousness of his in a matter of so great importance as this is, will not recommend him to the good esteem of any judicious Reader.</p>
               <p>But hitherto he hath brought his Authorities single, now he comes with whole Armies of them together. He tells us of whole Churches of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeans,</hi> or otherwise of the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> that were in the time of S. <hi>Jerom</hi> spread all over the <hi>East.</hi> This, saith <hi>M. N.</hi> is what S. <hi>Jerom</hi> shews in his 89th. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, which was to St. <hi>Austin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One that understands the <hi>Notitia</hi> of those times, can scarce tell where to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97513:25"/>find these pretended Churches which <hi>M. N.</hi> proposeth as Authorities for the <hi>Ʋnitarian</hi> Doctrine: And indeed it is in vain to look for them; for in a word, they were no other than Jews, such as were in the Body of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, who were by the Pharisees accounted <hi>Nazarens,</hi> and so condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Hereticks, because tho' they profest Judaism, they notwithstanding acknowledged Jesus Christ to be the <hi>Messias</hi> whom God had promised to their Nation. See the words of S. <hi>Jerom. Ʋsque hodie per totas Orientis Synagogas inter Judaeos haeresis est, quae dicitur Mineorum, &amp; à Pharisaeis nunc usque damnatur: quos vulgò Nazaraeos nuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant, qui credunt in Christum filium Dei natum de Virgine</hi> Maria, <hi>&amp; eum dicunt esse qui sub</hi> Pontio Pilato <hi>passus est &amp; resurrexit: in quem &amp; nos credimus: sed dum volunt &amp; Judaei esse &amp; Christiani, nec Judaei sunt, nec Christiani. There are at this time in all the Synagogues amongst the Jews of the East some Hereticks that go by the name of</hi> Minaei, <hi>who to this very day are condemned by the Pharisees and called</hi> Nazarens; <hi>they believe in Jesus Christ the Son of God born of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97513:25"/>Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and they say it was he who suffer'd under</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>and rose again the Third day from the Dead. This could be no other than the same Jesus in whom we believe. But while they would be both Jews and Christians, they become neither Jews nor Christians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Must he not have lost all sense of Shame that goes to impose thus upon his Reader? It is true, that S.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ʋpon</hi> Isa. C. V. <hi>v.</hi> 18.</note>
                  <hi>Jerom</hi> tells us, That the Jews curst the Christians in their Synagogues by the Name of <hi>Nazarens,</hi> and still to this day they give that Name to all that acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Jesus Christ to be the <hi>Messias;</hi> thinking thereby to perswade us, that because Jesus Christ lived at <hi>Nazareth,</hi> which was in the Tribe of <hi>Zabulon,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by consequence he could not be the promised <hi>Messias.</hi> But doth it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from thence that the <hi>Nazarens</hi> or the <hi>Minaeans,</hi> of whom S. <hi>Jerom</hi> speaks before, were not Members of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue? And being so they were properly Jews and not Christian <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have but one thing more to say in this place, of the Witnesses which <hi>M. N.</hi> brings against Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> being
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97513:26"/>afterwards to speak of the <hi>Cerinthians,</hi> of the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> and of the fifteen first Bishops of <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> But here I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take notice how he endeavours to impose upon his Reader,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ʋpon</hi> Euseb. L. V. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> when he quotes <hi>Valesius,</hi> and makes him say; that the Errors that were in the Books of some of the antient Writers, soon made their Works to be neglected, and at length to be totally lost. <hi>M.N.</hi> being now to hunt about for Witnesses, catcheth up these among the rest, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that all those whose works are perisht were <hi>Ʋnitarians,</hi> and among the rest he reckons <hi>Papias, Hegesippus</hi> and <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But he wrests the words of <hi>Valesius;</hi> for he speaks of Errors in general, and not particularly of those of the <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians.</hi> Tis a plain Mark that the thing was so; because its certain, that <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> was reckon'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Defenders of the Divinity of our Lord Jesus Christ, by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor that refuted <hi>Artemon</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Third Century, of whom there is a Fragment in <hi>Eusebius.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. V. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</note> I shall make the same appear of <hi>Hegesippus</hi> in what followeth, and it will be easie
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97513:26"/>to judge by Parity of reason that the like holds true of <hi>Papias.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>That neither the Authors of the</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Creed, <hi>nor</hi> Clemens Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus <hi>were of the opinions of the</hi> Unitarians.</head>
               <p>SINCE my principal Design is only to shew the vanity of <hi>M. N</hi>'s System, I shall not stay to examine what <hi>M. N.</hi> objects against Dr. <hi>Bull's</hi> Authorities. The Doctor, as he saith, brings his Authorities from forged pieces, which he makes use of as if they were Apostolical writings, such as, the Epistle of <hi>Barnabas, Hermas, Pastor,</hi> and the Epistles of St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> upon all which <hi>M. N.</hi> Criticizes to make a shew of his Learning in Antiquity.</p>
               <p>It would be ridiculous to enter the Lists with <hi>M. N.</hi> in a dispute concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Antiquity, or the Authority of those pieces that are quoted by Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> these Subjects having been sufficiently
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97513:27"/>handled by learned Men of the first Rank; and it is in vain for <hi>M. N.</hi> to expect, that his few petty Objections will carry the Point against their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments and Decisions.</p>
               <p>But for Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> it is enough to have proved that these pieces were written before the first <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> which the <hi>Socinians</hi> accuse of having innovated, and that they plainly teach the Doctrine which the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Nice</hi> have defined. This is what <hi>M. N.</hi> hath not ventured to deny.</p>
               <p>But let us suppose, if he pleases, and if he thinks it will do him any service, that these pieces were forged in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, or even in the middle of the second Centery, as <hi>M. N.</hi> pretends, doth it follow, that the Testimony of these Authors is of no value, or considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to prove that the Divinity of our Saviour was the current Doctrine of those times in which these pieces were written? <hi>M. N.</hi> hath very little Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Consideration if he thinks so.</p>
               <p>These, saith he, were forged pieces; but he cannot deny, First, But that they did hold a considerable Rank a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Ecclesiastical Books, in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97513:27"/>times before the first <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, and that many Churches read some of them publickly with great venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Secondly, If they were forged he cannot deny but that it was for some other end, than to make this Doctrine of Jesus Christ's Divinity to be receiv'd in the Church, one needs but read them to make him agree to all this.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Epistles, <hi>M. N.</hi> sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poseth that they were invented to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Authority of Ecclesiastical Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and from hence he takes occasion to shew his Talent in railing against the Clergy. But then that these pieces might pass for genuine, the Forgers of them must have spoke of the person of Jesus Christ, as he was generally spoken of in those times in which they lived. So that <hi>M. N.</hi> gets nothing by all this, unless he can pretend that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin Martyr,</hi> or some of his first Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples that made these counterfeit pieces, conform'd them to his own Principles and Opinions.</p>
               <p>But how wisely doth <hi>M. N.</hi> suppose, that <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> might take that piece which goes under <hi>Barnabas</hi>'s Name to have been written by <hi>Barnabas</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:97513:28"/>the Apostle, notwithstanding that the Writer of it plainly taught and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd that Doctrine of the Divinity of Christ; and yet <hi>M. N.</hi> in the Chapter next before, had affirm'd that <hi>Clemens</hi>'s <hi>Hypotyposes</hi> were slighted and lost for this reason, because they so much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded with the Seed of <hi>Arianism</hi> and <hi>Ʋnitarianism?</hi> After this we have no great reason to rely upon <hi>M. N</hi>'s Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>I shall not take notice of his insipid railleries upon <hi>Pionius</hi>'s Revelation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout St. <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Epistles. There are none but weak People that look upon it as truth. But one must make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self very ridiculous to take occasion from thence to doubt of <hi>Polycarp</hi>'s Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, which was asserted by the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> whereof he was Bishop, in their Epistle that is extant in <hi>Eusebius.</hi> Those that shew their Wit in taking advantages against Truths of History, from the Fables that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented in obscure times, shew they have very little strength either of Wit or Judgment. A Judicious Man will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways take care not to confound Truth with Fable, nor will he go to disprove
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97513:28"/>a Matter of Fact, or a certain Truth by a Fable that was tackt to it in after ages. For while he affects to make the ignorant laugh at the ridiculousness of the Fable, he will only stir up the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of the Lovers of Truth, who cannot endure to see it treated in that manner.</p>
               <p>I shall now consider the Witnesses that <hi>M. N.</hi> brings against us as of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contestable Authority, and which he saith, prove the Doctrine of the <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians</hi> to have been universally received by the Church in the time of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and of their Successors, until <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s time, whom he is pleased to brand with the Infamy of being an Innovator in the Christian Faith. To this end he musters up the Apostles as Authors of the Creed, St. <hi>Clemens Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi> a Disciple of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Primitive Churches that were planted by the Apostles, under the names of <hi>Nazarens, Mineans,</hi> or <hi>Alogians,</hi> and the Author of the <hi>Recognitions,</hi> who, if we may believe him, were all <hi>Ʋnitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we ask him, why he reckons the Authors of the Creed among the <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians,</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:97513:29"/>he tells us, that they have made no mention either of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> or of the Divinity of Jesus Christ; but that they have described our Lord Jesus Christ as a Man, though not as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon one because of his miraculous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. If we ask him, why he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that the Apostles were Authors of that Creed, he tells us, that <hi>Vossius</hi> and <hi>Dupin</hi> deny'd it was theirs, only because this Creed passeth over in silence the Mysteries which the Papists and Protestants look upon as the foundation of their Religion, and thereupon he takes a great deal of pains to confute <hi>Vossius</hi> and <hi>Dupin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is indeed a Question of no very great importance, whether or no the <hi>Apostles</hi> were Authors of this <hi>Creed.</hi> But setting aside that matter for the present, here are Matters of Fact to be considered.</p>
               <p n="1">1st. Though it is certain that the Apostles did teach their <hi>Catechumens,</hi> whether Jews or Pagans, an Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Christian Doctrine; yet no one hath spoke of it before <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who giveth us a form of Christian Doctrine
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97513:29"/>much differing from that which hath been in the Roman Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. We do not read that this form was in use among any of the Hereticks that were known in the first or second Century.</p>
               <p n="3">3dly. Most part of the Articles of the Creed were framed in opposition to the Heresies which arose in those Antient times. For example, the Article which saith that the Father of Jesus Christ was the <hi>Maker of Heaven and Earth,</hi> was oppos'd to the Heresie of <hi>Marcion.</hi> The Article that <hi>Jesus Christ is the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son of God,</hi> was oppos'd to the Heresie of <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> who held that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus was a meer Man, and that the Christ descended upon him in the shape of a <hi>Dove,</hi> and left him again when he was ready to die.</p>
               <p>Those that upon a critical Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Antiquity of the <hi>Creed,</hi> have deny'd that it was composed by the Apostles, had not the least thought of the design which <hi>M. N.</hi> layeth upon <hi>Vossius</hi> and <hi>Dupin.</hi> Nor could <hi>M. N.</hi> suspect them of such a design, unless he imagines, as there is reason to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97513:30"/>he does, that all the <hi>Trinitarians,</hi> and also the <hi>Arrians,</hi> have for above 1500 years repeated this Confession of Faith, without being sensible how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistent it was with their Belief, and that <hi>Vossius</hi> and <hi>Dupin</hi> were the only Men that did perceive it, yet did not dare to shew that they did; but left it to <hi>M. N.</hi> to discover what they thought, and he hath been so kind as to do it for them.</p>
               <p>Whatever we judge in this matter, if <hi>M. N.</hi> had thought of what he writ,</p>
               <p n="1">1st. He would have made the same reflection in this place, that he did in condemning <hi>Barnabas</hi>'s Epistle. There he proved that the Antients could not really believe it to be <hi>Barnabas</hi>'s; for if they had, they would have reckon'd it among the Canonical Books. This rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soning is just and solid, but it destroys all that <hi>M. N.</hi> hath writ, to prove that this Creed was composed by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, and that they dictated it in so many words; for where is that Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stastical Writer that ever reckon'd the Creed which we call the Apostles, among the Canonical Writings of the New Testament? And doth <hi>M. N.</hi> who is so
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97513:30"/>witty upon the Revelation of <hi>Pionius</hi> about St. <hi>Polycarp</hi>'s Martyrdom, take that for genuine, which we read in a Sermon that goes under the name of St. <hi>Austin,</hi> how every one of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles contributed his Article to make up the number of twelve in the body of this Creed?</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. What did <hi>M.N.</hi> think of, when he affirm'd so positively that <hi>Rufinus,</hi> who writ about the year of Christ 400. was the first that explain'd the Apostles Creed? Did not the Church of <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> pretend to teach their <hi>Catechumens</hi> the Apostles Creed, upon which their Bishop St. <hi>Cyrill</hi> writ his Exposition? Yet we see their Apostles Creed differs very much from that which we have in <hi>Rufinus,</hi> and <hi>Rufinus</hi> doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that his Apostles Creed was used any where else but in <hi>Italy.</hi> By what Authority can <hi>M. N.</hi> make it appear, that the Church of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> left off the Creed of the Apostles to be used by them of <hi>Aquileia,</hi> and framed another for themselves that was unknown to the rest of the Christian World?</p>
               <p>I believe <hi>M. N.</hi> will never be able to perswade any reasonable Man, that the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97513:31"/>Church, if it had receiv'd the Creed from the Apostles, in the same terms in which we have it, would ever have consented to let it be alter'd; nor would the Bishops have dar'd to substitute ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there having been one already at <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> nor would the People, who had learnt it before their admission to Baptism, have ever receiv'd another from them; at least the imposing of it would have caus'd terrible divisions.</p>
               <p>It is very well known how <hi>Arianism</hi> prevailed in the East for sixty years, all which time the <hi>Arians</hi> without doubt put another sense on that Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, <hi>And in Jesus Christ his only Son our Lord.</hi> But after all, the People retained the Orthodox Sense of the Article; and the Ears of the People that had been baptized into the belief of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> were more pure than the Lips of their Teachers that endeavoured to impose upon them.</p>
               <p>But is not <hi>M. N.</hi> wholly singular in his Judgment of this matter? He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, with his head full of the <hi>Ʋnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Opinions, to give us the sense of the Creed, and would make us believe that the Authors of it were <hi>Ʋnitarians.</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:97513:31"/>But they that first quoted the Creed as an Abridgement of the Doctrine of the Church, were of a far different opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; namely <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who was proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly as old as <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> not elder than he, and who wrote within twenty years after him, being Bishop of <hi>Lions</hi> at that time; and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who writ within fifty years of <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> and was very well read in the Writings of the first Christians. Yet both these were so far of <hi>Justin</hi>'s opinion, that they lookt upon those as Hereticks who would not acknowledge the eternal Divinity of Jesus Christ. How came they to strike in so early with <hi>Justin,</hi> and to suffer him so to impose upon them in so great a point of the Christian Faith? Were they so simple as not to discover that he put a quite different sense upon this Article from that which the Apostles designed when they made it, and which continued among all the Apostles Successors till the year of our Lord 150, which <hi>Irenaeus</hi> must needs have known, being then above thirty years of age when <hi>Justin</hi> writ, and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> though he was younger, could not but have read or heard of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:97513:32"/>
               <p> But not to rely only on the Authority of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> for the sense of that Article about the Person of Jesus Christ; we know the Jews understood very well the meaning of the words, <hi>Jesus Christ his only Son our Lord;</hi> for they knew, as may be seen in several places in <hi>Philo,</hi> that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Lord,</hi> was equivalent to that of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>God;</hi> only that the first expresseth the Empire of God. How much better then was it known to the Christians? who, as <hi>Pliny</hi> saith, in his time, before <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> was born, sang in their Assembly a Hymn to Christ, as God. The title of <hi>only Son</hi> is of the same power with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> among the Jews, as I shall shew from <hi>Philo,</hi> who often calls him the <hi>First-born;</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> represents him under the same Idea, as being <hi>Heir of all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>b. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and <hi>by whom God made the World;</hi> and therefore justly the Object of Adoration of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
               <p>Since we have not left us any Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Creed by the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> or the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> which they could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to have received from the Apostles, <hi>M. N.</hi> must pardon us if we stick to the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97513:32"/>Notions, which the Fathers declared that they did receive from the Apostles, I say such Fathers as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> who were the first that mentioned that Rule of Faith, especially since they are comformable to those Notions of the antient Synagogue, and to the Writings of the New Testament.</p>
               <p>But have we not reason to admire the Fickleness of <hi>M. N</hi>'s Judgment in letting himself discover a mighty Secret for an opportunity of shewing his Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks? He tells us there are shrewd Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptions, that to the Institution of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism by our Saviour in the Gospel of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> these words have been add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost.</hi> What are those Presumptions? He tells us only this one; It appears in the <hi>Acts,</hi> and Epistles of the Apostles, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles never baptized in that form of words, but only in the name of the <hi>Lord Jesus.</hi> But who told him that those words, <hi>In the name of Jesus,</hi> were the form in which they baptized? I should have thought those words had signified no more than baptizing them to be Disciples of Jesus, as <hi>baptizing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97513:33"/>into</hi> Moses, or <hi>baptizing in the name of</hi> Paul, signifies no more than bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them to be the Disciples of <hi>Moses</hi> or of <hi>Paul.</hi> And if these words were not the very form of Baptism, how can he say, that those other words, which Christ prescribed as his form, were never used by the Apostles, and therefore these words were foisted into the Gospel of S. <hi>Matthew</hi> by some Impostor? It would have been a very great satisfaction if he had told us whether he made this Discovery by comparing our S. <hi>Matthew</hi> with the <hi>Nazarens</hi> Copy, which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to be found in MS. in some Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braries. But this would be to ask too much of him; for though he will not allow us this form that is in S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> he doth at the same time admit of the Apostles Creed, which is really no more than that form of Baptism, or the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of believing <hi>in the Father, in the Son, and in the Holy Ghost,</hi> which they made before they were baptized.</p>
               <p>That which he tells us of S. <hi>Clement,</hi> is altogether new. <hi>Photias,</hi> saith he, and <hi>Petavius,</hi> and <hi>Huetius,</hi> three great Criticks, lament that S. <hi>Clement</hi> was only an <hi>Ʋnitarian;</hi> because he gives the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97513:33"/>Person of Jesus Christ but very mean Characters, and infinitely below those of Divinity. <hi>M. N.</hi> quotes some passa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Clement,</hi> which he thinks have nothing in them too high; and because S. <hi>Clement</hi> in his Epistle, where he quotes that glorious Description which S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath made in his first Chapter to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> did not quote the 8, 9, 10, 11, and 12th Verses, where Jesus Christ is called <hi>God,</hi> and where the <hi>Creation of the World</hi> is ascribed to him; tho' <hi>M. N.</hi> pretends thata convenient Solution may be put upon these words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ye he boldly affirms that it appears S. <hi>Clement</hi> acknowledged nothing in Christ more than Humanity; and that these five Verses of the first Chapter of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> might well have been added by the like fraud, that hath been used in many places of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and Gospels. His reason for it is, that S. <hi>Clement,</hi> who is said to have interpreted the Epistle of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> could not be ignorant of the great Title of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and would without doubt have exprest it, if he had designed to extol the Dignity of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of our Saviour.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:97513:34"/>
               <p> What a heap of false Suppositions is this? First, it is false that <hi>Photius</hi> believed S. <hi>Clement</hi> to be an <hi>Ʋnitarian.</hi> It is possible, that <hi>Photius</hi> might not observe in reading S. <hi>Clement</hi>'s Epistle, that he treats Jesus Christ as <hi>God.</hi> But if <hi>Photius</hi> did not give all the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention that he could in reading, doth it follow from thence that <hi>Clement</hi> was an <hi>Ʋnitarian?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">§. 1. &amp; §. 58.</note> We have by good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune S. <hi>Clement</hi>'s Epistle preserved to us, and we may judge of it our selves: when he wisheth, <hi>The Grace of God, and his Peace, may be multiplied through Jesus Christ,</hi> to them of <hi>Corinth;</hi> and adds at the end, <hi>the Grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all.</hi> What doth he mean, but that Jesus Christ may distribute the Grace of God?
<note place="margin">§. 16.</note> And is not that the Sense of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>that Grace and Peace may be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied from God, and from Jesus Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When he saith, that our Lord Jesus Christ, who is the Scepter of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty of God, did not come, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the Pomp of Grandeur and Pride, as he well might; but with all humilty, as the Holy Spirit had spoken of him <hi>Isaiah</hi> LIII; doth it not shew that he
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97513:34"/>followed the Description of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who tells the <hi>Philippians;</hi> that our Lord Jesus Christ <hi>being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God;</hi> or did not affect to seem equal with God, but <hi>made himself of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a Servant?</hi> Doth not this shew, that, according to S. <hi>Clement,</hi> our Lord Jesus Christ was in being before he chose the form in which he appeared?</p>
               <p>How can <hi>M. N.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">§. 21.</note> who doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that we ought to adore or call upon Jesus Christ, reconcile this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of S. <hi>Clemens,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <q>Let us pray to our Lord Jesus Christ, whose Blood was given for us?</q> For this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> properly signifies the Prayers that are made to God with adoration.</p>
               <p>What doth <hi>Clemens</hi> mean,
<note place="margin">§. 32.</note> when he saith that Jesus Christ was born of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> according to the flesh? Doth it not appear that he was well acquainted with S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s distinction, <hi>Rom.</hi> IX. 5. <hi>Whose are the Fathers, and of whom as concerning the flesh Christ came, who is over all, God blessed for ever, Amen?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:97513:35"/>
               <p> I don't mention that which he saith in §. 36. where he quotes the first of the Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> where S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who follows the terms of Wisdom, VII. 26. exalts him above the Angels, as being the Son of God, and ascribes to him an Empire over all things, such as is described in <hi>Ps.</hi> CX. of which Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire no Creture is capable.</p>
               <p>But I would fain know of what sort of <hi>Ʋnitarians M. N.</hi> will have <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> to have been? was he an <hi>Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite?</hi> No. For he is continually quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Writings of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> which the <hi>Ebionites</hi> rejected. Was he a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaren?</hi> No. For he quotes not only S. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Gospel according to our Greek Copy, but also the other Gospels, except S. <hi>John</hi>'s; which was not then written. Was he a <hi>Cerinthian?</hi> No. For he quotes the Writings of the Old Testament. Sure this must have been a strange sort of <hi>Ʋnitarian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know very well that <hi>M. N.</hi> observes that the title of <hi>Chief Priest</hi> is the most glorious Character that <hi>Clement</hi> gives to Jesus Christ, in his first Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which is that we speak of. But after all, he ought not to be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97513:35"/>ignorant, that that title in the stile of the first Christians, as well as the antient Jews, was the title of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This may be proved from several places of <hi>Philo.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quis rerum divin. haer. <hi>p.</hi> 509. <hi>B.C.</hi>
                  </note> But I shall content my self with quoting this one. <hi>Caeterum illi ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum principi Sermoni antiquissimo hoc eximium donum concessit Pater Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, ut in confinio stans, facturam à fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore discerneret. Idem supplex immortalem appellat pro mortalibus deprecans, &amp; à summo rege legatione ad subditos sungitur. Quod donum tam libenter accipit, ut jactet etiam, dicens,</hi> &amp; ego steteram medius inter vos &amp; dominum, <hi>videlicet nec ingenitus ut Deus, nec genitus ut vos, sed inter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trema medius, apud utrosque agens obsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem; apud Creatorem, ut sides siat nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam cum deleturum aut deser<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>rum uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versum genus revolutum in perturbationem ab ordine; apud creaturam vero, ut ea certam spem habeat, nunquam Deo propitio curam operis sui defore. Nam ego denuncio creaturae pacem ab eo qui bella tollit Deo, pacis custode perpetuo</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, it is not true, that the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> was written origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in Hebrew, though some of the Antients have thought so upon a very
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97513:36"/>light conjecture, because, say they, he must have written in Hebrew to those who were Hebrews by birth. One needs but read it attentively, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. with <hi>Coloss.</hi> 1. to see, that it is an Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and that it was written by S. <hi>Paul</hi> himself, as well as his other Epistles. No Man of Judgment, except <hi>M. N.</hi> could have thought otherwise, suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing that the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> to whom the Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> was directed, were so numerous in the East, because it highly reflects upon them to have lost the Original Tongue of that very Epistle, which was written to their Forefathers, and to have kept only the <hi>Greek</hi> Copy of it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is the highest presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to conclude, because S. <hi>Clemens</hi> quotes only that which goes before, and that which follows in the first Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that those five Verses were foisted in after the Epistle was spread abroad and better known. At this rate of judging by Quotations, one that would take the pains to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, might reject a great part of the Bible, and we could not be certain of any.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97513:36"/>
               <p> But saith <hi>M. N.</hi> the Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> was not reckoned a genuine piece of Scripture any where in the West, nor in many Churches in the East before the end of the fourth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury; and that might have made it the more easie to have been corrupted. In this he shews what it is to meddle with things that he doth not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand. It can't be denied, and this very Writer acknowledges, that <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> quoted this Epistle, in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle which he writ in the name, and by the order of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> so that by his own confession it was owned in the West in the Apostles times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who also writ in the West, quotes the Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews: Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> and S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who lived in <hi>Africa;</hi> all these quoted it as Canonical. But to put this matter out of question, S. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apostle is a Witness above all exception to prove that S. <hi>Paul</hi> writ an Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That which made several of the Antients doubt of its Authority to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the middle of the third Century, was the business of the <hi>Novatians,</hi> who
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97513:37"/>made use of its Authority to justifie their refusing to admit to publick Penance such as had faln into Idolatry to avoid persecution. But after all, if one seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously considers <hi>M.N</hi>'s method, it tempts one to wish that he was sent to preach the Gospel to the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> of whom some maintain, (as well as he) that the Gospels and Epistles have been cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the Christians in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that the Christians have soisted in what they pleased that made for their opinions.</p>
               <p>Now for another instance of <hi>M. N</hi>'s honesty, where Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> hath quoted a place in <hi>Clement</hi>'s second Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that might have solved the Objection. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The words signify, <hi>Brethren we ought so to think of Jesus Christ as of God, as of the Judge of the quick and the dead.</hi> There can no other Sense be put upon them, though <hi>M. N.</hi> saith they must be thus translated: <hi>Brethren we ought to think of Christ, as we do of God, namely, that he also is our Judge.</hi> If it is want of skill in the Greek that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97513:37"/>makes <hi>M. N.</hi> commit such Error, and rail so at Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> for his own Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; let the <hi>Socinians</hi> look them another Champion, for there is no Grammarian but will say he deserves to be whipt for construing it so. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.... and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are said of the same Person, if I know any thing of Grammar. <hi>Photius</hi> understood it as Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> hath, and <hi>M. N.</hi> thinks <hi>Photius</hi> sincere. But what need we care whether <hi>Photius</hi> was a good Grammarian or no.
<note place="margin">§. 10.</note> Doth not <hi>Clemens</hi> explain himself about the Preexistence of Christ, when he saith, Jesus Christ who hath saved us, <hi>being first a Spirit, and afterwards becoming flesh, and so he hath called us?</hi> No, saith <hi>M. N.</hi> let the Grammar be how it will, the Scriptures declare that Jesus Christ is Judge because he is a Man. Poor Man! Could he be capable of judging, that is to say, of knowing the Hearts, if he was but a Man? It is not said simply, as <hi>M. N.</hi> pretends it is, that Jesus Christ is to judge because he is a Man, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he is the Son of Man, by Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; he that is described by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> in the VIIth of his Prophesies, that is the <hi>Messias,</hi> who was to be so,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97513:38"/>the Son of Man, as to be also the Son of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>That the</hi> Nazarens, <hi>the</hi> Ebionites, <hi>the</hi> Minaeans <hi>and the</hi> Alogians, <hi>were justly looked upon as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Am now come to the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> the <hi>Minaeans</hi> and the <hi>Alogians;</hi> whom <hi>M. N.</hi> represents to us as the true Depositaries of the Faith of the Apostles: And he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to perswade us, that the Fifteen first Bishops of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and <hi>Hegesip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> who calls them Orthodox, and all the Bishops and People in the World that were in their Communion, were true <hi>Ʋnitarians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> having acknowledged, that if the Jews, who were converted by Jesus Christ and the Apostles in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daea,</hi> and who continued their Assemblies till the destruction of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> did
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97513:38"/>not own the Divinity of Jesus Christ, but believed him a meer Man, that Question is at an end between the <hi>Socinians</hi> and us. <hi>M. N.</hi> sets himself to prove; First, that the first Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were called <hi>Nazarens</hi> and <hi>Minae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in <hi>Judaea.</hi> Then he proves from <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> that the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> who observed the Law of <hi>Moses,</hi> and the <hi>Nazarens</hi> began at the same time. He saith, that the <hi>Ebionites</hi> were the same with them, only they had a different name; because, tho' some of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved Jesus to be born of the Virgin and of <hi>Joseph,</hi> and the rest acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged him to be conceived of the Holy Ghost without <hi>Joseph,</hi> they still agreed that he was but a meer Man, which was the reason of <hi>Origen</hi>'s saying that all the Jews that believed Jesus Christ to be the <hi>Messias</hi> were called <hi>Ebionites.</hi> From all this he concludes, that the first Disciples of Jesus Christ, and of the Apostles, rejected the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Divinity of Jesus Christ, and that the Body of these <hi>Nazarens,</hi> under the Government of the Fifteen first Bishops of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> preserved the true Faith of the Apostles touching
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:97513:39"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:97513:39"/>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:97513:40"/>the Person of Jesus Christ; that is as much as to say, they held the Opinion of the <hi>Ʋnitarians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not necessary to repeat what I have formerly said of the <hi>Minaeans,</hi> from the Testimony of S. <hi>Jerom</hi> in his 89th. Epistle to S. <hi>Austin,</hi> that they were in the Synagogue, and that they were not a Body of Christians. I shall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take notice, that the Name of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim,</hi> that is to say, <hi>Hereticks,</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver originally given to any People, Sect; or Party of Christians. It was the Name which the Pharisees gave to the Jews that were Sadducees: Afterwards the Pharisees gave it to those that rejected their Traditions, whom they looked upon as Hereticks for that reason. Afterward the Jews gave that Name to the Christians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause in teaching that Jesus was God they seem'd to destroy the capital Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Jewish Religion, which is the Unity of God. But most parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly they gave that name to such Christians, as, tho' they continued in Communion with them, did neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less acknowledge Jesus to be the <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sias.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97513:40"/>
               <p> As for the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> I acknowledge that the Christians were at first called by that Name in <hi>Judaea:</hi> But I deny that those, whom they afterwards call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Nazarens</hi> or <hi>Ebionites,</hi> were the Body of the Apostles Disciples, that were established at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> or in <hi>Palestine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To convince <hi>M. N.</hi> of this, I desire he will consider: First, That those who followed the Doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles in <hi>Palestine,</hi> were indeed called <hi>Nazarens,</hi> but only by the Jews; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they acknowledged Jesus of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth</hi> for the <hi>Messias,</hi> whom the Jews looked upon as a false Prophet. It is in this sense that they call the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Jesus Christ <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and their Doctrine an <hi>Heresie.</hi> [<hi>Act.</hi> 24.14.] In this sense they have continued to call the Christians <hi>Nazarens</hi> in that Curse which they pronounce in the Synagogue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all Christians, as <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> saith [against <hi>Trypho p.</hi> 323.]</p>
               <p>But this Name of <hi>Nazarens</hi> came af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward to have another signification among the Christians, as may be seen in the ancient Writers. And this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun without doubt after the Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Jesus Christ were called <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:97513:41"/>which was first at <hi>Antioch,</hi> as St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, in the <hi>Acts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed we do not see that the <hi>Nazarens</hi> were known after that time except among the Jews, who called the <hi>Christians</hi> so by way of reproach. <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit. An.</hi> 15. calleth them <hi>Christians</hi> hat were persecuted at <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Nero</hi> in the Year of our Lord 64. After that, <hi>Nero</hi> made Laws against them by the name of <hi>Christians. Pliny</hi> speaks of the <hi>Christians</hi> in <hi>Bithynia</hi> in <hi>Trajan's</hi> time. The Emperour <hi>Hadrian</hi> sent a Writing to <hi>Minucius Fundanus</hi> Pro-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sul of <hi>Asia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eus. H. E. IV. 9, 10.</note> in favour of the <hi>Christians.</hi> The Author of the Epistle to <hi>Diogne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> which is among the Works of <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> describes the Life of the <hi>Christians,</hi> but doth not call them <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarens,</hi> yet he calleth himself a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the Apostles. <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> witnesses that even all the Hereticks took the general name of <hi>Christians.</hi> And those whom <hi>Barchocba</hi> persecuted in <hi>Palestine</hi> are called Christians: But they are never called <hi>Nazarens</hi> by <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> who describes the Jews cruelties against them. Where then were the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> who were so fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97513:41"/>according to <hi>M. N.</hi> and who, if we may believe him, were the only true <hi>Christians</hi> in <hi>Palestine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> speaks of <hi>Nazarens</hi> as Hereticks;
<note place="margin">Haer. 29. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</note> but he can't decide whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they believed Jesus Christ to be a meer Man, or to be God. Indeed <hi>Irenaeus</hi> doth not speak of these <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> whom he would not have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born to call <hi>Hereticks,</hi> believing as he did the Divinity of Jesus Christ, if they had denied it in his time, and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if they had made any conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Body. <hi>Eusebius</hi> saith nothing of them. S.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>C.</hi> 4.</note>
                  <hi>Jerom</hi> mentions them in his Treatise of <hi>Ecclesiastical Writers,</hi> but doth not tell us their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Theodoret</hi> saith, that the <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> and the <hi>Ebionites</hi> were Hereticks, that appeared under the Reign of <hi>Domitian.</hi> It is plain, that these an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Doctors would not have been at such a loss to shew the Belief of the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> if there had been great Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches through all <hi>Asia,</hi> as <hi>M N.</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines. For these Fathers would (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt) have known these <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> and would have learnt their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions from the Books of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97513:42"/> 2dly. The primitive Names, such as that of <hi>Nazarens,</hi> are not always a mark of Succession in Doctrine. No one doubts that the Apostles Disciples were first called <hi>Christians</hi> at <hi>Antioch;</hi> and yet <hi>M. N.</hi> must acknowledge, that the Christians at <hi>Antioch</hi> and all over the World, held the same Faith with his pretended <hi>Nazarens</hi> at <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> How then should it come to pass, that <hi>Paulus</hi> of <hi>Samosata,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> should be condemned as an Heretick; who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>M. N.</hi> was a true <hi>Nazaren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3dly. How chanceth it that <hi>M. N.</hi> doth not observe what <hi>Epiphanius</hi> saith, that the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> and the <hi>Nazarens</hi> began at the same time? If by the <hi>Nazarens M. N.</hi> understandeth the first Disciples of the Apostles at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> they began immediately after our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour's Ascension, and not under the Reign of <hi>Domitian.</hi> As for the <hi>Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Epiphanius</hi> assures us, that they began at <hi>Antioch</hi> a little before the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> that is to say, about Seventeen years after our Saviour's Ascension. For if we may believe <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius,</hi> it was against <hi>Cerinthus</hi>'s Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, that the Assembly was held at
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97513:42"/>
                  <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> But after all, the antient Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which is delivered by <hi>Irenaeus</hi> from the mouth of <hi>Polycarp,</hi> saith,
<note place="margin">Lib. III. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> that <hi>Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus</hi> was rejected at <hi>Ephesus</hi> by S. <hi>John;</hi> probably after his return from <hi>Patmos,</hi> that is after the Year of our Lord 96.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly. How can <hi>M. N.</hi> reconcile all this with what he says, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Creed was the rule of Faith in this Primitive Church? Were the <hi>Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> or the <hi>Symmachians</hi> (who believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Jesus Christ to be born of <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi>) also of the Body of the Apostolical Church,
<note place="margin">Orig. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. V. <hi>p.</hi> 272. <hi>&amp;</hi> 274.</note> and reckoned true <hi>Nazarens?</hi> This was a strange Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. The <hi>Ebionites</hi> had the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Creed. Then they believed Jesus Christ to be conceived of the Holy-Ghost, and born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and notwithstanding communicated with such, as believed Jesus Christ to be born of <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5thly. Is <hi>M. N.</hi> in earnest when he saith, That <hi>Origen</hi> maintains that all the Jews who acknowledged Jesus Christ to be the <hi>Messias</hi> were called <hi>Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> and that the <hi>Ebionites</hi> are <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> and consequently the antient School of the Apostles? Hath he forgot that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97513:43"/>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> accounted the <hi>Ebionites</hi> to be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks?
<note place="margin">Orig. <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi> Cels. L. V. <hi>p.</hi> 272.</note>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> is forced to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that he accounted them such; and so he calls them and distingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes them from the Church.</p>
               <p n="6">6thly. What doth <hi>M. N.</hi> think of, when he condemns <hi>Epiphanius</hi> for say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the <hi>Ebionites</hi> rejected S.
<note place="margin">L. III. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note>
                  <hi>Pauls</hi> Epistles,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Againct.</hi> Cel. L. V. <hi>p.</hi> 274. Haeret. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bul. L. II. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> and called him an Apostate? Doth not <hi>Irenaeus</hi> say the same thing. And <hi>Origen</hi> in his piece against <hi>Celsus?</hi> The like is also related by <hi>Theodoret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7thly. I should be glad to know, if the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> or the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> or the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> were the same with those in the Apostles times, whom the Jews called <hi>Nazarens.</hi> Why doth not <hi>M. N.</hi> receive the Gospel of the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> and why doth he reject it, as Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphal and Superstitious. Did these first Christians, who ought to have served for a Pattern to all others, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a Gospel that was rejected by the other Sects?</p>
               <p n="8">8thly. It would be well if <hi>M. N.</hi> would let us know how S. <hi>Matthew's</hi> Gospel, such as we have it with the Genealogy of Jesus Christ, and S. <hi>Lukes</hi> Gospel came to be received as Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97513:43"/>after they had been rejected as supposititious Peices by the <hi>Ebionites</hi> and the <hi>Symmachians,</hi> who were both of them <hi>Nazarens?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9thly. How came it to pass that the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> that is, the true <hi>Ʋnitarians,</hi> continued in Communion with the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> who affirmed that S. <hi>John</hi>'s Gospel was written by <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> and not by S. <hi>John</hi> the Evangelist?</p>
               <p>But it is time now to undeceive <hi>M. N.</hi> if it be possible, and to give him a more faithful Account of the <hi>Cerinthians,</hi> and of the <hi>Ebionites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. I. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> than that which he hath set before us. See what <hi>Irenaeus</hi> saith of them. <hi>Cerinthus</hi> asserted, that the World was not made by God, but by a certain Virtue whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly different, and very far from that Principality which is over all things, and which knew nothing of the God that is over all. As for Jesus Christ, he believed it impossible that he should be born of a Virgin, and therefore taught that he was born of <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> like other men; tho' he did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell other men in Prudence and in Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. He saith, that the Christ de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended upon Jesus, from the Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97513:44"/>which is over all things, in the Likeness of a <hi>Dove,</hi> and then Jesus Christ revealed the Father, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was not known; and that at last Christ, who was not capable of suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, forsook Jesus, and left him to suffer Death.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> their Doctrines were not altogether so impious, but they received no other Gospel but S. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s, and rejected the Apostle S. <hi>Paul</hi> as an Apostate. They observ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the Ceremonies of the Law, and lived as Jews, and adored <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> as being the house of God. This is what <hi>Irenaeus</hi> saith of them;
<note place="margin">Ibid. L. I. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note> who also ascribes to them the Belief that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ was born of <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> which was common to them with the <hi>Cerinthians:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. III. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> And saith that in this they followed the Doctrine of <hi>Aquila,</hi> and of <hi>Theodotion.</hi> If there was any of them afterward, who believed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ to have been conceived of the Holy Ghost without <hi>Joseph,</hi> they must have received this Belief after <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s time.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De earne Christi, c.</hi> 18.</note> For he speaks of them as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> doth.</p>
               <p>How can <hi>M. N.</hi> forbear blushing for
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97513:44"/>his Folly, in looking on these People as the Disciples of Jesus Christ and his Apostles, and affirming that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Church was composed of such execrable Wretches? Could such as these receive the Apostles Creed? Could they look upon the Apostles as their Masters? Could they pass for Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the Judgment of any Man, that is himself a Christian? <hi>M. N.</hi> ought to think himself obliged to those that defend the Trinity, and the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of our Saviour, for having deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the World from these people, who rejected the most Sacred Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Christian Faith; and for having preserved to the Evangelists and Apostles the right which Jesus Christ had given them of being the Teachers of his Religion.</p>
               <p>As for the pretended Gospel of S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> which was in the hands of the <hi>Nazarens,</hi> it is easie to convince <hi>M. N.</hi> that he hath spoken at random when he builds so many things upon what he had heard of it. If he had been acquainted with S. <hi>Jerom</hi> his Works, he would have found some Quotations out of that Gospel of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97513:45"/>
                  <hi>Nazarens,</hi> which would have undeceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. S. <hi>Jerom</hi> cites that Gospel in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. in <hi>Isai.</hi> 8. and in <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. and brings these words, as the words of our Saviour; <hi>Modo me arripuit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mea, Spiritus Sanctus. Now my Mother the Holy Ghost hath possessed me.</hi> I am sure <hi>M. N.</hi> will never find these words in the true Gospel of S. <hi>Matthew.</hi> And for the sense of them, as it depends upon the knowledge of the Jewish Tradition, which <hi>M. N.</hi> condemns and despises so much, it will be a Riddle to him for ever, although they are easily understood by those who are acquainted with the Jewish Notions.</p>
               <p>After all, when <hi>M. N.</hi> is pleased, to make all the Christians that came out of the Synagogue to be called <hi>Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi> and grounds his Assertion upon a passage of <hi>Origen,</hi> who saith, that those among the Jews, who received Jesus Christ for the <hi>Messias</hi> are called <hi>Ebionites;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. L. II. <hi>p.</hi> 56.</note> he imposes upon his Reader. For <hi>Origen</hi> doth not say, that these Jews left the Synagogue to make se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate Assemblies.
<note place="margin">Ib. Contr. Cels. L. II.</note> What Author ever did say so? <hi>Origen</hi> speaks of people
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97513:45"/>that lived in the Body of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue; much like what S.
<note place="margin">Jer. <hi>Ep.</hi> 89. <hi>ad</hi> Aug.</note>
                  <hi>Jerom</hi> saith in the passage that I have quoted. And indeed <hi>Origen</hi> exposes <hi>Celsus</hi> for his ignorance, in making a Jew speak to Jews that were converted to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity, otherwise then he ought to have done, for want of knowing that these Jews whom the Christians called <hi>Ebionites</hi> continued in the Body of the Synagogue, and observed the Laws of it. Tho' otherwise they confessed that Jesus Christ was the <hi>Messias</hi> promised to their Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>That neither</hi> Hegesippus, <hi>nor the Fifteen first Bishops of</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>were of the opinion of the</hi> Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, <hi>or the</hi> Ebionites: <hi>And that the</hi> Alogi <hi>were Hereticks as well as the</hi> Cerinthians.</head>
               <p>IT is easie to be judged from all this; how solidly <hi>M. N.</hi> refutes Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> who maintains from a passage in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesippus</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:97513:46"/>that the Fifteen first Bishops of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> were Orthodox, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Divinity of Jesus Christ; and that all the other Bishops in the World, and particularly those of <hi>Rome</hi> were Orthodox, because they held Communion with the Bishops of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> pretends on the other side: 1st. That <hi>Hegesippus</hi> in his accounts of Hereticks, doth not account the <hi>Cerin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> and the <hi>Ebionites</hi> among the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks: From whence it follows that he did not think them Hereticks, but Orthodox, and therefore <hi>Hegesippus</hi> was himself of their Opinion.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. That this appears, because <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesippus</hi> was a Jew by Nation; that all the Jews converted to Christianity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ebionites,</hi> according to <hi>Origen, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesippus</hi> was also a <hi>Nazaren</hi> or an <hi>Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite;</hi> and that the <hi>Nazarens</hi> being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by <hi>Hegesippus</hi> to be Orthodox, therefore the Fifteen first Bishops of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> must have been <hi>Nazarens,</hi> and that all the rest of the Christian World was <hi>Nazaren,</hi> because in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them.</p>
               <p>It is enough to put one out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97513:46"/>to have such a Man to deal with. <hi>M. N.</hi> saith <hi>Hegesippus</hi> was an <hi>Ebionite,</hi> that is, denied the Divinity of Christ. What Proof does he bring for this? He was originally a Jew. I will grant it him if he pleases. And that <hi>Hege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sippus</hi> mentions S. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Gospel in Hebrew: I grant that also. But what then? Will <hi>M. N.</hi> from thence inferr, that <hi>Hegesippus</hi> was an <hi>Ebionite?</hi> That is a small piece of Sophistry. The <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionites,</hi> who were Jews of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, had in Hebrew a Book which they called S. <hi>Matthews</hi> Gospel; but it was not the same that we all now make use of. For the <hi>Ebionites</hi> had taken the liberty to cut off the genealogy of our Saviour, and what else they pleased out of S. <hi>Matthews</hi> Gospel, and had added to it what they thought fit, as I have shewn by S. <hi>Jerom</hi> his Testimony. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>Hegesippus</hi> was a Jew by Birth, that he was therefore an <hi>Ebionite:</hi> What a consequence is this? He was not a Jew of the Synagogue, but a Christian by profession; and he might as well make use of the pretended S. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in Hebrew, as S. <hi>Jerom</hi> could tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slate it into Latin without being an <hi>Ebionite.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:97513:47"/>
               <p> Secondly, <hi>Hegesippus</hi> converss'd at <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Anicetus, Eleutherus,</hi> and <hi>Soter,</hi> and found them of the same opinion with the fifteen first Bishops of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem:</hi> So according to <hi>M. N.</hi> all the other Bishops in the World, who were in their Communion, were <hi>Ebionites</hi> and <hi>Nazarens.</hi> If this consequence were good, I wonder how <hi>Hegesippus</hi> came to say, that the Church was pure from Heresie no longer than till the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the second Century. He ought to have said that the Church had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served her virginity till this time, that is till the year 170. Whereas he saith expresly, that the Hereticks peep'd out of their holes, and began to corrupt the Apostles Doctrine immediately after their Deaths.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, If <hi>Hegesippus</hi> did not take the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> for Hereticks, how came it to pass that he continued for so long a time in Communion with the Roman Bishops, namely with those three great Bishops <hi>Anicetus, Eleutherus,</hi> and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi> For that these Bishops accounted them Hereticks, it sufficiently appears from <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who accounted them Hereticks; and was not in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97513:47"/>only, but in high esteem with those three Bishops, as well as was <hi>Pothinus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Lions,</hi> whom he succeeded in his Bishoprick.</p>
               <p>But, saith <hi>M. N. Hegesippus,</hi> giving an account of the Hereticks of his time, did not reckon the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> among them; and <hi>Valesius</hi> was in the wrong to insert the words, <hi>Et alii,</hi> to take them in. But herein <hi>M. N.</hi> betrays his Ignorance as well as his Rashness. <hi>Hegesippus</hi> speaks of the Sects that were among the Jews before Jesus Christ, and shews that from them arose several Hereticks among the Christians: Such as the <hi>Simonians,</hi> the <hi>Menandrians,</hi> the <hi>Marcionites,</hi> the <hi>Carpocratians,</hi> the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinians,</hi> the <hi>Basilidians,</hi> and the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnilians.</hi> Was he obliged to speak of all the Hereticks, when he was only speaking of those which owed their Original more immediately to the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies of the Synagogue?</p>
               <p>But besides, it is easie to convince <hi>M. N.</hi> of the falseness of his position, as to <hi>Hegesippus</hi> his Belief.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> It is certain that he came to <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of <hi>Anicetus,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in the year 150, and he lived there
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97513:48"/>at <hi>Rome</hi> to the time of <hi>Eleutherus,</hi> who began in 170, and died in the year 185. This is what <hi>Eusebius</hi> tells us,
<note place="margin">L. IV. c. 2.</note> that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesippus</hi> himself witnesseth. He declares that he lived in the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and of its Bishop. Now this Bishop was of the same opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who was in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, and who reckoned the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> and the <hi>Ebionites</hi> to be Hereticks; therefore <hi>Hegesippus</hi> reckoned them Hereticks as well as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> did.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is certain that <hi>Justin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> who died at <hi>Rome</hi> under persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was always lookt upon as Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox in the Questions about the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Jesus Christ. Now he is the first that treated of Heresies, and writ an History of their Authors.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Et in</hi> Eus. H. E. IV. 2.</note> He witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth it himself in his Apology. Those that came afterward, as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> who writ against Heresies in <hi>Eleutherus</hi>'s time,
<note place="margin">L. III. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> as appears from himself; and <hi>Hippolytus,</hi> who as far as we can judge followed him, did but copy from <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin.</hi> Now it is certain that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Hippolytus</hi> accounted the <hi>Cerinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and the <hi>Ebionites</hi> Hereticks after <hi>Justin Martyr.</hi> Therefore the Church
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97513:48"/>of <hi>Rome,</hi> in which <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Hippoly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> lived for many years in great credit, and consequently <hi>Hegesippus</hi> accounted the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> and the <hi>Ebionites</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
               <p>To avoid this consequence, it must be supposed that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> changed its opinions all on a sudden after <hi>Hegesippus</hi> his departure from <hi>Rome;</hi> that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> changed in like manner, with all the Christian <hi>Gauls;</hi> that those who were Orthodox in <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s time, became all of them Hereticks in the space of fifteen or sixteen years; and that, when a small difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Western Churches about <hi>Easter-day,</hi> had troubled the peace of the Church, and given occasion for se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Assemblies of the Bishops to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this difference, all the Churches changed their Faith almost in a night, without perceiving it, without making the least reflection, or being at all moved: The <hi>Catechists</hi> changed their Instructions to the <hi>Catechumens;</hi> the Bishops the stile of their <hi>Sermons,</hi> and of their Christian <hi>Common Prayers;</hi> those that writ against the Jews and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans altered all their Ideas, and the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97513:49"/>whole method of the Controversie: All the People changed the form of their Prayers; and in a word, that all went to bed, <hi>Ebionites</hi> and <hi>Cerinthians,</hi>and did awake in the opinions of <hi>Justin Martyr;</hi> and all this when most part of them had never heard of <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s Books, nor of his Conference with <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew, in which <hi>M. N.</hi> saith that he advanceth new Hypotheses a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Person of our Saviour Jesus Christ.</p>
               <p>We are now come to the <hi>Alogi,</hi> whom <hi>M. N.</hi> takes for the Christians that were converted from Pagans, as those that were converted from Jews accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him were <hi>Nazarens.</hi> So taking into the number of the old <hi>Ʋnitarians,</hi> all those that were converted by Jesus Christ and his Apostles. He supposes then that they bore the name of <hi>Alogi,</hi> because they denied the <hi>Logos</hi> or <hi>Word,</hi> of which S. <hi>John</hi> speaks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> is the first that hath men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned the <hi>Alogi;</hi> and he gave them that name of his own head, as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares twice in his Refutation of them; and, as <hi>M. N.</hi> himself acknowledgeth. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> tells us that they appeared
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97513:49"/>after the <hi>Quartodecimans;</hi> that is, after the year of our Lord 190. They a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted the opinions of <hi>Cerinthus</hi> and <hi>Ebion,</hi> which had made Jesus Christ to be a meer Man, and to be born of <hi>Joseph</hi> and <hi>Mary.</hi> Against which opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions S. <hi>John</hi>'s Gospel and his Epistles were written, as saith <hi>Irenaeus;</hi> and these pieces giving their Disciples some trouble, they set themselves to elude the force of them. First, to make the three first Gospels contradictory to S. <hi>John</hi>'s, to destroy the authority of it. And, Secondly, they were so ridiculous as to assert that that Gospel and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation were written by <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> and not by S. <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is probable that <hi>Epiphanius</hi> would by this term of <hi>Alogi,</hi> intimate such Hereticks as rejected S. <hi>John</hi>'s Gospel and the Revelation: both because they rejected the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and because they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Gifts of the Holy Ghost, and the Prophesie times promised in the Gospel. For <hi>Irenaeus</hi> speaks of certain Hereticks without naming them, of whom he saith:
<note place="margin">L. III. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 259. <hi>C.</hi> D.</note>
                  <hi>Alii vero ut donum Spiritus frustrentur quod in novissimis Temporibus secundum placitum Patris effusum est in humanum
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97513:50"/>genus, illam speciem non admittunt, quae est secundùm [Joannis] Evangelium, in qua Paracletum se missurum Dominus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misit; simul &amp; Evangelium, &amp; Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum repellunt spiritum. Infelices [verè] qui Pseudoprophetae quidem esse volunt, Prophetiae verò gratiam repellunt ab Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia: Similia patientes his, qui propter eos qui in hypocrisi veniunt, etiam à fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum communicatione<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se abstinent. Datur autem intelligi, quod hujusmodi neque A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolum</hi> Paulum <hi>recipiant. In ea enim Epistola quae est ad Corinthios de Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticis charismatibus diligenter loquutus est, &amp; scit viros, &amp; mulieres in Ecclesia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetantes. Per haec igitur omnia peccan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in spiritum Dei, in irremissibile incidunt peccatum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>These however are the People that <hi>M. N.</hi> calls the body of the Pagans that were converted to Christianity. He represents them to us, as the body of the Church; and his proof for it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>Theodotus</hi> about the year 190, forsook the party of the <hi>Platonick</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, who believed the Preexistence of our Saviour, and joined himself to the <hi>Alogi.</hi> And after this, he spits his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom at <hi>Eusebius,</hi> for affirming that <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odotus</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:97513:50"/>was the first that made Jesus Christ a meer Man.</p>
               <p>What Injury hath poor <hi>Eusebius</hi> done to <hi>M. N?</hi> He was according to <hi>M. N.</hi> a great <hi>Ʋnitarian;</hi> though he calls <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samosata,</hi> (the <hi>Ʋnitarians</hi> Favourite) an Heretick and Disciple of <hi>Artemon. Eusebius</hi> hath not said one word of what <hi>M. N.</hi> ascribes to him concerning <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odotus:</hi> He only relates a pretty long passage out of an Author that had writ in the beginning of the third Century against the Heresie of <hi>Artemon,</hi> a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Ʋnitarian.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us. <hi>H.E.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. V. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</note> This nameless Author saith that <hi>Theodotus,</hi> whom he looks upon as the first Author of the <hi>Ʋnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> Doctrine, was excommunicated by Pope <hi>Victor;</hi> from whence he infers that <hi>Victor</hi> was not of the <hi>Ʋnitarians</hi> opinion as they supposed him to be, pretending that their Belief had been the general opinion of the Church, and of the Apostles Successors, until the time of <hi>Victor</hi> and of <hi>Zephyrin,</hi> Bishops of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But how doth all this prove that the <hi>Alogi</hi> were the Pagans that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by the Apostles? They are Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that rejected the Gospel of St. <hi>John,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:97513:51"/>his Revelations and Epistles, as the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> had done. That is, they were <hi>Cerinthians;</hi> or if you please they were those who are described by <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> as a sort of Hereticks. <hi>Theodotus,</hi> as <hi>M. N.</hi> truly saith, being excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated by <hi>Victor,</hi> went over to their party; what then? doth this prove that they were the body of the Church that were converted by the Apostles from among the Gentiles? It certainly shews that they resolved not to acknowledge the Godhead of Jesus Christ; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thought they must reject the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel of S. <hi>John,</hi> and his other Writings. And yet they shewed more honesty in doing so than the <hi>Socinians,</hi> who have thought that they might receive S. <hi>John</hi>'s Gospel, and yet deny the Divinity of Christ, which <hi>Julian</hi> the Apostate, confess'd to be clearly expressed by S. <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After all, I cannot but wonder how <hi>M. N.</hi> can think of the choice of Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses that he hath made to confirm his System, without being ashamed of them himself. The <hi>Nazarens</hi> who were his converted Jews, received no other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel but that of S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> and that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97513:51"/>very much adultered. The <hi>Ebionites,</hi> who were another sort of his converted Jews, rejected all the Epistles of S. <hi>Paul.</hi> The <hi>Alogi,</hi> who were his Gentile-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, rejected all the Works of S. <hi>John.</hi> And all this for the Hundred and fifty first years of Christianity, and something longer. How then came the Books of the New Testament to be afterwards so well received at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and in <hi>Judaea?</hi> And how came they to be after that so well known all over the World?</p>
               <p>By <hi>M. N</hi>'s reckoning, the <hi>Trinitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> that were born after <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s time, must have come and opened the eyes of the Apostolical Churches among the Jews, and also among the Gentiles; for it was by them that the Apostolical Books came to have their due authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And therefore let <hi>M. N.</hi> magnify his Primitive <hi>Ʋnitarians</hi> as much as he will, he shall never perswade any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering Man to believe, that they who made so bold with the Apostles, as to reject so many of their Books, did not also reject what they pleased of the Apostolical Doctrines; or that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Doctrines were not preserved by
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:97513:52"/>them that rescued out of the hands of those Hereticks so many of those Books which the <hi>Socinians</hi> do now acknowledge to be Divine Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The last Monument or Remain of the Apostolical Succession, which agrees with the Socinian Doctrine concerning our Saviour, saith <hi>M. N.</hi> are the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognitions,</hi> ascribed to <hi>Clemens Romanus.</hi> He calls the Author of these, an <hi>Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite;</hi> though he believeth it was a piece falsly put under the name of <hi>Clement. M. N.</hi> doth very well to shew his fair dealing in this. He hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected <hi>Barnabas, Hermas,</hi> and <hi>Ignatius,</hi> as suppositious Authors, and therefore of no authority in this Controversie. And yet now he gravely quotes these <hi>Recognitions</hi> as a monument of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical Succession. Is there not a great deal of Justice in this? But then, it seems, others of the Primitive <hi>Ʋnitar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> were Forgers, as well as <hi>Cerinthus;</hi> he was not the only Man of this trade, though perhaps he was the first of them; for he forged Revelations and Visions under the name of S. <hi>John,</hi> which gave the occasion to them, that as <hi>M. N.</hi> elsewhere observes, would
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97513:52"/>have <hi>Cerinthus</hi> to be the Author of the Revelation. Now here is another of their gang that forges a Book under the name of <hi>Clemens,</hi> the Disciple of the Apostles.</p>
               <p>But how came <hi>M. N.</hi> to know that the Author of the <hi>Recognitions</hi> was an <hi>Ebionite?</hi> he tells us, he took <hi>Dupin</hi>'s word for it. But he would have done better to have read the <hi>Recognitions</hi> himself, and then he would have seen that this Author favours the <hi>Arians,</hi> and not the <hi>Ebionites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this it appears with how much vanity, and how little reason, <hi>M. N.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all the Successors of the Apostles were <hi>Ʋnitarians.</hi> He doth indeed quote a long passage of the Author that writ against the <hi>Artemonites,</hi> in the beginning of the third Century, who saith that those Hereticks had the insolence to affirm this: For they boast that their Doctrines continued in peaceable possession of the Churches that were planted by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, and by their Successors, till the times of <hi>Victor</hi> and of <hi>Zephirin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the same Author confutes them with several Arguments. 1. From the authority of Scripture. 2. From the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97513:53"/>Works of some of the Fathers whom he quotes, such as <hi>Justin, Miltiades, Tatian, Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria, Irenaeus,</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito.</hi> Whereupon <hi>M. N.</hi> observes that <hi>Justin</hi> who lived in the middle of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Century, is the first that he hath named; and from thence he infers that <hi>Justin</hi> was the first that set up the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Divinity of Jesus Christ. A pretty piece of Sophistry! as if the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of five or six of the Fathers who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the Godhead of Jesus Christ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Victor</hi> and <hi>Zephirin</hi>'s time, was not amply enough to destroy the assertion of <hi>Artemon,</hi> which was the thing he design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to confute. If <hi>Artemon</hi> had been of his opinion, would not he have been a fool to put off the beginning of the Doctrine of our Saviour's Divinity to the time of <hi>Victor,</hi> who lived above thirty years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s death?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:97513:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>That</hi> Justin Martyr <hi>was no Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is nevertheless upon this ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous foundation, that <hi>M. N.</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to prove that <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> was the first that innovated; in affirming that it was the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that appeared to the antient <hi>Patriarchs</hi> under the Old Testament, and that was called by the name of <hi>Jehovah;</hi> from whence he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the Pre-existence, and the Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Word.</p>
               <p>To shew that <hi>Justin</hi> was an Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and asserted this without ground, <hi>M. N.</hi> brings divers considerations up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on several passages of the Old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where it is said that <hi>God appeared,</hi> or that <hi>God spoke;</hi> in which passages the <hi>Socinians</hi> endeavour to prove that it was an <hi>Angel,</hi> and not <hi>God</hi> that is spoken of. And besides, he brings the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of some of the Antients, and late
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:97513:54"/>Writers, that contradict <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> about these notions.</p>
               <p>But he doth this with very little judgment: For the question is not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Justin</hi> brings some proofs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Pre-existence and Godhead of the <hi>Word,</hi> that the other Orthodox Fathers did not think fit to make use of; but whether <hi>Justin</hi> was the first that advanced this Doctrine among the Christians, being the product of his own Brain, and before unheard of. His Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogue with <hi>Trypho</hi> plainly shews the contrary: It was writ about the year 140. He there sets forth the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> or the <hi>Cerinthians,</hi> as People that made no great body among the Christians; which would have been very imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in one that had first brought up the opinion of the Godhead and Pre-exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence of our Saviour: and the Jew would have laught at him for proposing to him the belief of a Doctrine that he had never heard of before from any other Christian.</p>
               <p>But, in truth, that the Christians held this Doctrine of the Godhead of Jesus Christ was known to the Pagans, as appears by <hi>Pliny</hi>'s Epistle to <hi>Trajan,</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:97513:54"/>and the <hi>Philopatris</hi> that is among <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi>'s works; where the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and of the <hi>Godhead of Jesus Christ,</hi> and of the <hi>procession of the Holy Ghost,</hi> is set forth and explained by that scoffing Heathen, as dictinctly as it is at this day by any Orthodox Divine; and it was known to the Jews to be an opinion of the Christians, and that a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal one; as appears by <hi>Justin</hi>'s Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue with <hi>Trypho.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Controversie between <hi>M. N.</hi> and the Church, turns upon this question, whether <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> was an Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor or not; that is, whether the Doctrine of our Saviour's Pre-existence is the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Doctrine of the Apostles, and the Primitive Christians? Or whether we have abandoned the Faith of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and first Christians, and taken up a phantastical notion that was invented by <hi>Justin Martyr?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This question being of so great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, ought to be considered with a more than ordinary attention. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin</hi> presented his first Apology, which is the second in his Works now extant, to the Emperor <hi>Pius</hi> in the year of our Lord 139. He afterward writ his
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97513:55"/>Dialogue against <hi>Trypho,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains a dispute with a Jew about the truth of the Christian Religion. This appears,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dial. p.</hi> 340.</note> because in his Dialogue he speaks of his Apology. <hi>Justin</hi> lived at <hi>Rome</hi> afterward till he writ his se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Apology, (the first in his Works) and in the year of our Lord 150. he suffer'd Martyrdom there, being prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by <hi>Crescens</hi> an Heathen Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher.</p>
               <p>Here is a Man of great eminence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Christians of his time, who lived in the Metropolis of the Roman Empire in the times of <hi>Hyginus, Pius,</hi> and <hi>Anicetus,</hi> being Bishops there; and who was so far of their Communion, that his Pen served twice to stop the fury of two Persecutions by two famous Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies that he wrote in behalf of the Christians.</p>
               <p>In his first Apology, representing to the Emperor the Faith that was then profest by the Christians, he saith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly, that they believed the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and also the Incarnation of the <hi>Word:</hi> which shews that it was not a new Doctrine, unheard of before that time, nor such as came then into <hi>Justin</hi>'s head
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97513:55"/>while he was writing his Dialogue with <hi>Trypho.</hi> It is also to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served that this <hi>Justin,</hi> who defended the <hi>Trinity,</hi> in his Dialogue against <hi>Trypho,</hi> doth no less maintain the <hi>Ʋnity</hi> of God, as he hath done also in his Treatise of <hi>the Monarchy of God;</hi> though our <hi>Ʋnitarians</hi> can't tell how to reconcile this with the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He writ his Dialogue against <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho</hi> about the year 140. For in that Dialogue he sheweth plainly, that the Jewish War was then but newly ended. He lived ten years after in the eye of the World, and writ se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Books after this; so the Church could not but be fully acquainted with his opinions. But for all that, he continued peaceably in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of those great Bishops, whom <hi>M. N.</hi> calls <hi>Nazarens, Cerinthians,</hi> and <hi>Ebionites,</hi> and his memory is still bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed among Christians.</p>
               <p>But this is not all; for during his abode at <hi>Rome</hi> he lived in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with <hi>Polycarp,</hi> Disciple of S. <hi>John,</hi> who came thither under the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97513:56"/>Emperor <hi>Pius,</hi> and was in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Roman Bishop <hi>Anice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> He learnt (without doubt) from <hi>Polycarp</hi> the abhorrance which S. <hi>John</hi> had for <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree that he would not go into the House where <hi>Cerinthus</hi> was bathing, for fear it should fall upon their heads. He was also in Communion with <hi>Hegesippus,</hi> who came to <hi>Rome</hi> while <hi>Anicetus</hi> was Bishop there, and continued there till the time of <hi>Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therus.</hi> That there was an acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance between them, is more than probable. For <hi>Justin,</hi> though a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan before his conversion, was born in <hi>Samaria</hi> then called <hi>Neapolis;</hi> and <hi>Hegesippus</hi> was also a Native of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestine. Hegesippus</hi> witnesseth that he communicated with <hi>Anicetus,</hi> with <hi>Soter,</hi> and with <hi>Eleutherus;</hi> and that then all the Churches were in the same Faith. After this, how can <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> be looked upon as an Innovator?</p>
               <p>But to go to the bottom of <hi>M. N</hi>'s System, let us consider it a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97513:56"/>
                  <hi>Justin</hi> writ a Book against Heresies, which was the common store-house of all those Fathers that writ next after him upon that Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; as <hi>Irenaeus, Hippolytus,</hi> &amp;c. Now these Writers agree in treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> and the <hi>Ebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> as pernicious Hereticks. See <hi>Irenaeus, L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 25, 26. and the Latin Dialogue of the Heresies that is in the end of <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s Book of Prescriptions, which is but an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment of the Book of <hi>Hippoly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> Now it is certain, that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> as well as <hi>Hegesippus</hi> lived in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Roman Bishop <hi>Eutherus,</hi> and <hi>Eleutherus</hi> had lived in Communion with the foregoing Bishops that had communicated with <hi>Justin Martyr;</hi> it follows therefore that in those times, <hi>Justin</hi> was never looked upon as an Innovator.</p>
               <p>One needs but read the Dialogue with <hi>Trypho,</hi> to be satisfied that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin Martyr</hi> defends in it the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apostles, and of the whole Church till his time.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:97513:57"/> 1st. When he represents his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version to Christianity, he tells us, that it was by the Instructions of an old Man whom he did not know, and whom he met with in a Solita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place, whither he was retired to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate upon Philosophy.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. <hi>Justin</hi> reckons all those as Hereticks, who were distinguished by the Names of their Masters, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naming any: But there were none at that time whom this Character fitted better than the <hi>Ebionites</hi> and <hi>Cerinthians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3dly. <hi>Justin</hi> (as I have said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) doth mention a sort of Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters among Christians, plainly mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Ebionites;</hi> and represents them as a very small number in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of the generality of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,
<note place="margin">Just. <hi>p.</hi> 267.</note> that believed the <hi>Godhead</hi> of our Saviour.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly. <hi>Trypho</hi> doth from the Unity of God raise an Objection against the belief of the Trinity that was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the Christians,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 269, 7.4.</note> and looks upon the belief of that small num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97513:57"/>namely of the <hi>Ebionites,</hi> to be the most consistent with reason.</p>
               <p n="5">5thly.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 268.</note> If there had been no other Christians but <hi>Ebionites,</hi> at the time of this Conference of <hi>Trypho</hi> with <hi>Justin,</hi> nothing could have been more impertinent than <hi>Trypho</hi>'s question, whether those that observed the Law, and withal acknowledged Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ to be the <hi>Messias,</hi> were capable of being saved? For the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bionites</hi> did both observe the Law, and receive Jesus as the <hi>Messias.</hi> And they according to <hi>M. N.</hi> were the Body of the Christian Church.</p>
               <p n="6">6thly It appears that the Christians went by no other Name in the time of <hi>Justin,</hi> then that of <hi>Christians:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ib <hi>p.</hi> 287.</note> and not by that of <hi>Nazarens,</hi> as <hi>M. N.</hi> supposeth.</p>
               <p n="7">7thly. <hi>Justin</hi> doth every where lay it down for a Rule, that <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> is the Object of Divine Worship for all Christians.</p>
               <p n="8">8thly. <hi>Trypho</hi> derides Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in general, because it teaches the <hi>Incarnation of the Word</hi> in the Womb of the Virgin, whereas for his
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97513:58"/>part he should have thought it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable to have acknowledged him to be only a Man, who upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Justice had been raised to the Dignity of <hi>Messias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9thly.
<note place="margin">Ib. <hi>p.</hi> 291, 292.</note>
                  <hi>Justin</hi> doth generally speak with horror against divers Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies that had then risen up against the Church according to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours prediction.
<note place="margin">Ib. <hi>p</hi> 307, 308.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10thly. He constantly represents the Christians of his time, as being endowed with the gift of Miracles, and the power of casting out De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils in the Name of Jesus Christ,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 311.</note> as of the true God. A Power, which we do not read that the <hi>Ebionites</hi> or <hi>Cerinthians</hi> ever had, or did ever pretend to it: And which <hi>Irenaeus</hi> made a distinguishing Character be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Catholick Church and all Heretical Assemblies.
<note place="margin">Iren. L. IV. <hi>c.</hi> 45.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11thly. <hi>Justin</hi> protests that the Christian Faith which he defends is the same that was spread all over the World,
<note place="margin">Just. M. <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. p.</hi> 345.</note> even in the most barbarous and unknown Countries: Which certainly he would not have
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97513:58"/>dared to affirm in the face of all Jews and <hi>Ʋnitarians,</hi> if they could have disproved him, and especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if there had been so many <hi>Ʋni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarian</hi> Churches as <hi>M. N.</hi> hath ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined.</p>
               <p>Now when I look back upon all these Considerations, I can't per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade my self that <hi>M. N.</hi> hath ever read the Dialogue between <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin</hi> and <hi>Trypho.</hi> I rather believe that he hath read in <hi>Eusebius,</hi> that <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> was the most antient Author that the Anonymous of the Third Century quoted, to prove the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Trinity and of the Godhead of the <hi>Messias</hi> was taught before the time of <hi>Victor,</hi> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated <hi>Theodotus</hi> of <hi>Byzanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um;</hi> and that thereupon he imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, though without ground, as I have shewed, that <hi>Justin</hi> was the Author of the Doctrine of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and of the Divinity of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. And as <hi>M. N.</hi> is a Man of extraordinary Confidence, he thought he might venture this System abroad,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97513:59"/>since it would be so highly accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to those of his Party, and would seem very specious to all others that could not gain-say, or that would not take the Pains to examine it.</p>
               <p>The especial Charge against <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> is this, That he was the first that ventured to say, it was the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that appeared to the Patriarchs and Fathers of the Old Testament, which according to the <hi>Socinians</hi> was either <hi>God,</hi> or an <hi>Angel</hi> that spake as Ambassador from God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently as God. And if so, it then followeth that <hi>Justin</hi> was an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novator.</p>
               <p>But they are much mistaken in thinking that <hi>Justin</hi> advanceth any new thing in affirming the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be a Divine person, and in saying it was he that appeared to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when he hath the Apostles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the first Chapter to the Hebrews, and S. <hi>John</hi> in the Preface of his Gospel, affirming that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Word, was God, and that it was he by whom the World
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97513:59"/>was created, and <hi>without whom was not any thing made that was made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He hath likewise, both in the one and in the other, followed the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Divinity of the Jews, such as we find it in the Writings of <hi>Philo,</hi> who writ before S. <hi>Paul</hi> and S. <hi>John;</hi> and in a time when the Jews had not invented the Evasions, which <hi>Justin</hi> reproaches them with in his Dialogue with <hi>Trypho.</hi> Now <hi>Philo</hi> doth positively affirm, That it was the <hi>Word</hi> who appeared to <hi>Abraham</hi> and to <hi>Sarah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18.</note> and whom <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> calls his <hi>Lord.</hi> He also affirms, that he was the same who appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Hagar</hi> in the Desart, and who changed the name of <hi>Jacob</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Israel.</hi> Which <hi>Word, Philo</hi> indeed sometimes calls an <hi>Angel,</hi> but he calls him also the <hi>Son of God, begotten of God,</hi> and his <hi>first born.</hi> I shall quote the places in the next Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>One would think that this being so well known to the Jews, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by so many several places in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:97513:60"/>
                  <hi>Philo, M. N.</hi> might have spared his accusing the Christians of having foisted the name of <hi>Christ</hi> in the 9. <hi>Ver.</hi> of the X. <hi>Chapter</hi> of the 1. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to confirm their Doctrine of the Pre-existence of Jesus Christ; whereas in the antient Copies it was, <hi>Let us not tempt God,</hi> as <hi>Grotius</hi> pretends it ought to be read according to the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Manuscript.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> confesseth that <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> charges this upon <hi>Marcion,</hi> and not on the Orthodox Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. But I do not see what reason <hi>Epiphanius</hi> could have to accuse <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> of this; for <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who was more antient than the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuscript, hath quoted the passage in these Terms,
<note place="margin">Iren. IV. 35. <hi>p.</hi> 385.</note>
                  <hi>Let us not tempt Christ;</hi> and surely <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who is there dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting against the Heretick <hi>Marci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> whom he accuses of having fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sified the Epistles of S.
<note place="margin">L. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note>
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> would take care not to use the Copies which <hi>Marcion</hi> had falsified.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly. Supposing in some Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script they had read the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97513:60"/>as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> would have it instead of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the mistake might easily be committed in Manuscripts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in such common words they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally writ only the first Letters K or X with a <hi>v</hi> over the Head. And is not the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> sufficient to denote <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> according to the ordinary Style of the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? It is certainly so, according to <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> who saith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that <hi>Christ and Lord denote the same person.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> Will not allow of this gloss of <hi>Epiphanius;</hi> but he would oblige us in shewing that which <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> did not; namely, what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of <hi>Marcion</hi>'s it could serve, to change the term of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> into that of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; for it is not credible, he would corrupt the Text only for his pleasure, and not to serve any design. But this change was so far from serving <hi>Marcion</hi>'s Hypothesis; that it would have been quite on the contrary. He denied that the <hi>God</hi> of the Old Testament was the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97513:61"/>Father of <hi>Jesus Christ.</hi> He rejected the Old Testament, and could not endure it should be said, that the Jews were under the care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> whom he set forth as the Author of a Gospel that was opposite to the Law and the Prophets. It was therefore contrary to his Design to make that corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Text which <hi>Epiphanius</hi> charges him with by changing <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. into <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which overturned all these Principles. According to him the Jews never had any thing to do with Jesus Christ; but whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depended upon the Creatour of Heaven and Earth, whom <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> would not allow to be the Father of our Saviour Jesus Christ. And therefore to make the Apostle say, that the Jews tempted Jesus Christ in the Wilderness had been to make the Apostle speak against himself. It was with the some de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign that instead of reading, <hi>but with many of them God was not well pleased,</hi> he had put, <hi>but Christ was not well pleased with many of them.</hi> But he had
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97513:61"/>not carried his falsification far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, for which <hi>Epiphanius</hi> laughs at him, for he had left these terms that the <hi>Rock was Christ,</hi> which was sufficient to justifie the reading of <hi>Irenaeus, Let us not tempt Christ,</hi> against the Authority of the <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> Manuscript. This, I hope, is enough to shew with what rashness <hi>M. N.</hi> asserts, that it is only since the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have taken advantage of this corruption of <hi>Marcion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:97513:62"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>That the Notion of the</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>did not come from the</hi> Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks, <hi>but was the antient No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Synagogue, and of the Apostles of our Saviour.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHAT I have said in general of the Doctrine of <hi>Philo,</hi> who was the most considerable of the Jews at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and lived under <hi>Caligula,</hi> to whom he was sent by his Nation as their publick Agent or Orator, is sufficient to shew, that the Notion of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and of his appearings under the Old Dispensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was no new Doctrine, nor first advanced by <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> in his Dialogue with <hi>Trypho.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheless <hi>M. N.</hi> either for want of due consideration, or in hopes of carrying it off by the help of his Criticks, doth obstinately maintain
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97513:62"/>that <hi>Justin</hi>'s Notion of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a <hi>Platonick</hi> Notion; and that though it was afterward adopted by some Christians, yet it was not known to the Apostles and their next Successors.</p>
               <p>What Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> quotes from the Jewish Writers to prove, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> was known to the Jews, is in no wise satisfactory to our Author. He saith that those Jews were all of them, either Phantastical <hi>Cabalists,</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators</hi> upon the Writings of the Old Testament; but Men of no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or Persons obscure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, such as <hi>Rabbi Tanchuma;</hi> or they were Christians that writ under the name of Jews, as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Books that go under the Name of <hi>Philo.</hi> Now let us see whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>M. N.</hi> hath any ground for being so very confident.</p>
               <p>The Notion of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, saith <hi>M. N.</hi> is a <hi>Platonick</hi> Idea, that was adopted by some Christians. This is a very bold Assertion. He takes the Liberty to say what he pleases
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:97513:63"/>of Books, that go under the name of <hi>Philo,</hi> which I have already quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But all that he saith is meer Talk without Proof. And it were strange if all the World reject Books that have not been questioned for so many Ages, because an angry Man resolves to cry them down.</p>
               <p>Let us but see what <hi>Philo</hi> saith of the Subject we now treat of, and then let any equitable Reader judge, whether <hi>M. N.</hi> hath reason to accuse <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> of having advanced <hi>Platonick</hi> Ideas, when he speaks of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>What follows, is the Doctrine of <hi>Philo</hi> concerning this Subject; which I have reduced to some Heads to avoid repetition; and I have quoted the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts of his Works for it, which it would have been too tedious to transcribe.</p>
               <p>He saith, that though, there be but one God, yet there are in him two Sovereign <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Powers,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97513:63"/>his Goodness or Bounty, and his Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>issance. His <hi>Goodness</hi> by which he hath created, and his <hi>Puissance</hi> by which he governs, and that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word</hi> is a third Power, by which he unites those two other Powers: So that it is by the <hi>Word,</hi> that he is both powerful and good. And he saith, that the two <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims</hi> were the Symbols of this truth.
<note n="a)" place="margin">Philo <hi>de Cher. p.</hi> 112. <hi>E. de confus. Ling. p.</hi> 337. <hi>de Migr.</hi> Abrah. <hi>p.</hi> 367. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He represents the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Word,</hi> as being infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to God, but without being distant from God; and so being he that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns those two Divine Powers, both that which Creates and that which Rules, and so that governs all. Which, saith he, was typified by the Presence of God above the <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims.</hi>
                  <note n="b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De profugi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, p.</hi> 466. <hi>B. C. D.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He saith, that it was the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word,</hi> that form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97513:64"/>and created the World.
<note n="c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Mundi Opif. p.</hi> 4. <hi>D. &amp; p.</hi> 5. <hi>C. &amp; Alleg.</hi> L. I. <hi>p.</hi> 44. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </note> And that it was the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that was the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> of God to form the World.
<note n="d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Cher. p.</hi> 129. <hi>C.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He calls the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Image</hi> of God;
<note n="e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Mundi Opif. p.</hi> 6. <hi>C.</hi>
                  </note> and saith it was by him that he formed the World,
<note n="f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Monar.</hi> L. II. <hi>p.</hi> 823.</note> and that he governs it.
<note n="g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Migr.</hi> Abr. <hi>p.</hi> 389.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He affirms, That these words, <hi>Let us make man in our own Image,</hi> shew that God took in others to work with him.
<note n="h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Op.</hi> M. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>C. De cons. Ling. p.</hi> 336. &amp;c.</note> and the Image of God in Man is the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word</hi> which is eternal.
<note n="i)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Plant.</hi> Noe <hi>p.</hi> 217. <hi>A.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He saith that the Soul was formed after the <hi>Image</hi> of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word.</hi>
                  <note n="k)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Opif. Mund. p.</hi> 32. <hi>E.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He saith, That the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word,</hi> is as the house that God dwells in.
<note n="l)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Migr.</hi> Abr. <hi>p.</hi> 389. B. <hi>De Somniis p</hi> 574. <hi>E. &amp; p.</hi> 575. <hi>B.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:97513:64"/>
               <p> He shews plainly enough, that in the VIII. of <hi>Prov.</hi> he understood by the Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God there spoken of, a <hi>Person,</hi> and not an <hi>Atttribute.</hi>
                  <note n="m)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Alleg.</hi> L. <hi>p.</hi> 48. <hi>A. p.</hi> 52. <hi>A,</hi> B.</note> Where he saith also, that it is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Word of God.</hi>
                  <note n="n)" place="margin">Ib. <hi>p.</hi> 54. <hi>E. &amp; lib. quod deter. pot. insid. p.</hi> 165. <hi>C.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He saith, that the <hi>Word</hi> is the <hi>Interpreter</hi> of God, that he was begotten of God, and that he giveth <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony</hi> to us from God.
<note n="o)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Alleg. Leg.</hi> L. II. <hi>p.</hi> 99. D, <hi>E.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He saith, that the <hi>Word</hi> is also called an <hi>Angel.</hi>
                  <note n="p)" place="margin">Ib. <hi>p.</hi> 39. <hi>D.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He affirms, that it was the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word,</hi> that appeared to <hi>Abraham</hi> and to <hi>Sarah,</hi> Gen. 24. and whom <hi>Sarah called my Lord.</hi>
                  <note n="q)" place="margin">Ib. <hi>p.</hi> 101 <hi>D.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He affirms, that it was the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that appeared to <hi>Hagar</hi> in the Desart
<note n="r)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De profug. p.</hi> 451. B. <hi>&amp; de Somniis p.</hi> 600. <hi>D.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:97513:65"/>
               <p> He saith, it was the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that changed <hi>Jacob</hi>'s name, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.
<note n="s)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De nomin. mut. p.</hi> 1088.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He saith, that the <hi>Manna</hi> typified the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Word of God.
<note n="t)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Alleg. Leg.</hi> L. II <hi>p.</hi> 93. B. <hi>Quod det. pot. insid. p.</hi> 176. <hi>E. De profug p.</hi> 470. <hi>A.</hi> B. L. III. <hi>Leg. Alleg.</hi> 1103. B.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He giveth an Idea of the <hi>Eternal Generation,</hi> when he affirms, that of that which is Divine there is nothing cut off, but only it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.
<note n="u)" place="margin">L. <hi>Quod det. pot. ins. p.</hi> 172. <hi>A.</hi>
                  </note> And when he speaks of the Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit without its being divided.
<note n="w)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De Gigant. p.</hi> 287. <hi>C.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>He affirms, that it is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word,</hi> that is the Son of God; whom the Prophet <hi>Zechary</hi> calls <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens.</hi>
                  <note n="x)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De conf. Ling. p.</hi> 329.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He saith, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word</hi> is the true High Priest, of whom the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent High-Priests were but Emblems.
<note n="y)" place="margin">
                     <hi>De prof. p.</hi> 666. B, C, D. <hi>de Somn. p.</hi> 597. <hi>C. De vit.</hi> Mos. L. III. <hi>p.</hi> 673. <hi>C.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:97513:65"/>
               <p> He sets forth the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Word,</hi> as the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor between God and Man at the time of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge.
<note n="z)" place="margin">
                     <hi>L. quia rerum div. h. p.</hi> 509. <hi>B. C. De vit. M. L.</hi> III. <hi>p.</hi> 673. <hi>C.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>I believe after this, <hi>N. M.</hi> is not very well satisfied in the care that hath been taken in preserving the Works of <hi>Philo.</hi> But though they had been all lost, the Truth, which <hi>M. N.</hi> opposes with such bold and yet vain conjectures, would not have suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered much by it. For <hi>Philo</hi> was but one Jewish Doctor, though he flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish'd in the time of our Saviour Jesus Christ. But I should be glad to know <hi>M. N</hi>'s thoughts of an Author of a quite different character from <hi>Philo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth he believe that the Gospel according to S. <hi>John</hi> was written by S. <hi>John,</hi> or by <hi>Cerinthus?</hi> He that believeth the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> to have been Apostolical Men, must believe S. <hi>John</hi>'s Gospel and the <hi>Revelations</hi> to have been the Work of <hi>Cerinthus,</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:97513:66"/>and not of S. <hi>John.</hi> No, saith <hi>M. N.</hi> the present <hi>Ʋnitarians</hi> acknowledge the Gospel and the Revelations to have been written by the beloved Disciple of Jesus Christ, that hath given them those lights, which the <hi>Cerinthians</hi> and the <hi>Alogians</hi> had not.</p>
               <p>I am very glad it hath: but how can <hi>M. N.</hi> after this maintain that the notion of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a <hi>Platonick</hi> Idea? Is it likely that S. <hi>John,</hi> who, setting aside the advantages he had by being the Disciple of Christ, was but an honest Fisherman, had read the Works of <hi>Plato?</hi> Was <hi>Plato</hi> known to the Fishermen upon the Lake of <hi>Tiberias?</hi> or were his Works translated into <hi>Syriac,</hi> which was the only Language they knew? If not, then it is a strange extravagance in <hi>M. N.</hi> to suppose that the notion of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a <hi>Platonick</hi> Idea. S. <hi>John</hi> was no doubt well acquainted with the Writings of the Old Testament, and what he said of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or Word, with plain reference to the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97513:66"/>first Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> and other places of the Old Testament; he learnt it not in the School of <hi>Plato,</hi> but in that of the Holy Ghost, who inspired him, and who was the same that dictated the Books of the Old Testament.</p>
               <p>But after all, is this stile only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to S. <hi>John,</hi> who was the last E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelist that writ? The Evangelist S. <hi>Luke</hi> is quoted by <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> as well as the Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> both as Canonical Books; and we know that they speak of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. I. Heb. X. Joh. I. Rev. XVI.</note>
                  <hi>Justin</hi> also quotes the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of S. <hi>John,</hi> both Gospel and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations. And in all these, there is mention of the <hi>Word</hi> in this notion; the Pre-existence and Godhead of the <hi>Word</hi> is plainly set forth in them. <hi>Socinus</hi> endeavours to elude the proof of it in S. <hi>John</hi>'s Gospel, by explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the word <hi>beginning</hi> by the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Gospel. <hi>M. N.</hi> corrects <hi>Socinus</hi> for that, and agrees with us that the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> signifies the Virtue by which God created the World, and only differs from us in the question,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97513:67"/>whether that all-creating <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Word</hi> was a Person.</p>
               <p>After this, it is easie to judge with what reason or sense <hi>M. N.</hi> rejects the Authorities that Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> brings to shew that the notion of the Pre-existence of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, was not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the Jews at the time when S. <hi>John</hi> writ. For my part I can't but wonder, setting raillery aside, how he could satisfie himself with what he brings to evade the force of Dr. <hi>Bull</hi>'s Arguments.</p>
               <p>The Jews, saith he, believed the <hi>Messias</hi> was to be a meer Man, as it appears by the Books of the New Testament, and by those of <hi>Justin Martyr.</hi> From thence he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, that the Jews before Christ's time believed nothing of the <hi>Pre-existence</hi> of the <hi>Messias;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the passages drawn from the Books that were written before Christ's time, particularly from the Wisdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> are of no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority against the Jews to prove
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:97513:67"/>that they have varied from their Fore-fathers in their notions of the <hi>Messias.</hi> If this reasoning is good, then Christ and his Apostles did them wrong in charging the Jews with so many Errors, on this account, of their corrupting of the Ideas of their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> sheweth that in the Book of Wisdom, there are notions of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that brought up <hi>Israel</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and that he was a Divine Person in the judgement of the Writer of that Book. <hi>M. N.</hi> can't deny this, but he hath two ways to make it signifie nothing. The first is, by speaking of that Divine Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son with a scurrilous Wit. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, by bearing us down with a conjecture of <hi>Grotius,</hi> that though this Book was written by a Jew, yet some Christian or other, who was a Greek, happening on it, hath given it us in the Greek Tongue, but with divers additions to it taken from the Christian Religion. For the first of these, it proves nothing
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97513:68"/>but what we know already, that <hi>M. N.</hi> presumes there are Readers that will be scoft out of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. For the second, it is certain that this Book in Greek as we have it, was quoted by <hi>Philo</hi> the Jew
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seb. <hi>de Praep. Ev. p.</hi> 323. Clem. <hi>ad Cor.</hi> §. 3, <hi>&amp;</hi> 27.</note>, and <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> and afterwards at least forty times by the Fathers of the second Century, who look'd upon it as a Book of undoubted An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity. And it seems very probable, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> did reflect on a passage in this Book, (<hi>Wisd.</hi> VII. 26.) when he was writing his Epistle to the <hi>Colossians, Col.</hi> II. 15. and again in the Epistle to the <hi>Hebrews, Heb.</hi> I. 3. which places <hi>M. N.</hi> may consider at leisure. The Jews therefore that were converted to Christianity must have known this Book; and look'd upon it as a Book that contained the antient Sentiments of their <hi>Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the Jewish <hi>Cabala,</hi> or Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which the Learned Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> recommends to his Reader, it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their traditional Sense of Texts
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97513:68"/>of their Scriptures, which they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently understood of the <hi>Messias.</hi> Now for this sort of Jewish Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is certainly of great use to them that are to dispute against the Jews. But if <hi>M. N.</hi> will not be so just to allow this Tradition, all the World is not so obstinate as he. We find in the antient Writings of the Jews such express notions of the Doctrines which the <hi>Socinians</hi> dispute against, that they either must have been forged by Christians, or the Jews before Christ's time must have had quite other notions of these mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters than those which the modern Jews have. We agree that these notions were not those of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People; and it appears plain enough from hence, that when Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ spoke of himself in such terms, the Jews could not but see that he attributed <hi>Divinity</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; the multitude who expected a mighty Conqueror for their <hi>Messias,</hi> seemed surprized at it, and were ready to stone him. These Traditions that we speak of, were the Ideas of such
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:97513:69"/>as had taken more pains in studying the Sacred Writings, and had col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the sense of them by attentive Meditation. That this was so, we learn from <hi>Philo</hi> the Jew, who makes a great difference between the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of the Law that they gave to the People whom he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and those which they reserved for such as had attained to a greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of knowledge in the Mysteries of their Religion. This may be seen in his Treatise <hi>de Sacrif.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Sacr.</hi> Ab. <hi>&amp;</hi> C. <hi>p.</hi> 153. <hi>B. Ed.</hi> Paris. <hi>A.D.</hi> 1640.</note>
                  <hi>Abel. &amp; Cain,</hi> where he is shewing the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God in events, which the Pagans look'd upon as meerly acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> doth like himself in abusing Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> and puting tricks upon his Reader, when he bears him in hand that these traditional Expositions of the Scripture were the very same that were rejected by our Saviour, and exclaims against the Doctor for using Arguments against the <hi>Socinians</hi> that are drawn from a Law, which was set up by the <hi>Pharisees,</hi> and condemn'd by Jesus Christ.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:97513:69"/>
               <p> Indeed if we admitted of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of the Jews before Christ's time, as a part of Divine Revelation that is not contained in the Books of <hi>Moses, M. N.</hi> would have reason to bring the authority of Christ against such Jewish Traditions. But here is a quite different case now. The Jews having stiffled those antient notions of a <hi>Messias,</hi> that according to their Prophesies was to be God as well as Man, we make it appear from the Books of their Ancestors, which were left, and which contain the Old Explications of their Synagogue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Christ's time, that they had such Explications, as they are now forced to reject, or else they must yield up the cause to the Christians.</p>
               <p>Now what hath <hi>M. N.</hi> to say a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our use of such traditional Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions? He either must deny that we have a right understanding of the old Jewish Paraphrases, or that they are not so antient as they are reputed, or else he must acknowledge
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:97513:70"/>that the Jews, who are now of the same opinion as himself concerning the nature of the <hi>Messias,</hi> have alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their belief concerning it since our Saviour's time.</p>
               <p>I shall not endeavour to refute what <hi>M. N.</hi> saith to take away the authority of two Hebrew Books that Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> quotes for the confirming of those Expositions. <hi>M. N.</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his great stock of Learning, calls one of them an <hi>obscure Rabbi,</hi> and the other the <hi>unknown Book Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kumam.</hi> The obscure <hi>Rabbi</hi> that he speaks of is <hi>Moses Bar Nachman,</hi> commonly called <hi>Ramban</hi> or <hi>Moses Girundensis,</hi> one of the highest note among the Jewish Commentators. The unknown Book called not <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kuman,</hi> but <hi>Tanchuma,</hi> is as well known among the Learned Jews, as any of their antient Books that are now extant. <hi>M. N</hi>'s ignorance of these things might well be excused; for he was not bound to understand Hebrew: yet we must needs tell him, that it is not very modestly done of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97513:70"/>him to pass a Judgement upon Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors that he neither knoweth, nor is able to understand.</p>
               <p>I will not spend time in answering what he saith of the Works of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> the Jew, that they were written by one <hi>Philo</hi> a Christian, who lived in the second Century after Christ. This is truly an unknown <hi>Rabbi</hi> to all Mankind but <hi>M. N.</hi> for he is the first that ever mentioned him. But he shews by his Critical Remarks on this occasion, that he hath as little skill in Christian Antiquity, as he hath shewn in Hebrew Writers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philo</hi> speaks frequently of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that was imployed by God in the Creation of the World, and in the Production of his other Works. Now the question is, whether he bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed this notion from the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> or from the <hi>Platonicks?</hi> That is easie enough to be decided, because what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever he says of this matter, he always grounds it on the Books of <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets, without once mentioning <hi>Plato</hi> upon the Idea of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:97513:71"/>
               <p> I ought also to observe that <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus,</hi> who hath many quotations out of <hi>Philo</hi>'s Works, of which some are lost, reckons him not a <hi>Platonick</hi> but a <hi>Pythagorean.</hi> But certainly <hi>M. N.</hi> must have lost his reason, if he maintains that the Works which bear the name of <hi>Philo</hi> were written by a more modern Author than him that writ the Apology for the Jews to <hi>Caligula,</hi> whom <hi>M. N.</hi> can't deny to have been <hi>Philo</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> that went to <hi>Rome</hi> as their Agent within seven years after Christ's Death. The Style, the Notions, the quotations from his other Writings, and what other Authors who lived after him have quoted from him, are to a Reader of any ordinary judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment such convincing Arguments, that they were written by the same Author, that one that will go about to prove the contrary loses his time and his labour, and so will he that giveth him an answer.</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant that some of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:97513:71"/>the Antients after <hi>Eusebius</hi> have ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, that <hi>Philo</hi> did in his Treatise of the <hi>Therapeutae</hi> describe the first Christians of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and some of them have gone so far as to say, <hi>Philo</hi> might have seen S. <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and turn Christian. But all this is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but meer groundless ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination; they are such vain conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures that those that attentively read <hi>Philo</hi>'s Works, and particularly what he saith of the <hi>Therapeutae,</hi> and that have any knowledge of Church-Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, can't but pity those that let such Fathers opinions be imposed upon them by the name of <hi>Eusebius</hi> and his Followers.</p>
               <p>I believe I have by this time suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently answered all that is worth considering in <hi>M. N</hi>'s <hi>Judgement of the Fathers.</hi> According to the Scheme that I proposed. I did not think it worth my while to take notice of several faults that are here and there in his Work, but fall immediately upon the principal ones; my chief design being to shew the False<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:97513:72"/>and Absurdity of his System, which I presume to say I have done.</p>
               <p>I have not taken notice of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusation which he comes up with very often, <hi>viz.</hi> that those of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Party were always Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; because it is so notoriously false, that there was no need of refuting it. <hi>M. N.</hi> confesseth that the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and of the Divinity of our Saviour, was publickly and generally received af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s time; and that the Primitive Christians still lived under Persecutions from the Pagan Emperors till <hi>Constantine</hi>'s time. What therefore can he mean by this accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation against the Defenders of the Trinity? The first Persecutions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to blood that can be found any where among Christians, were by the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> and those <hi>M. N.</hi> himself is pleased to reckon among his <hi>Ʋnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi> With what confidence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can he affirm so false a thing, as that is that the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> hath been kept up only by Violence and Persecution?</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:97513:72"/>
               <p> But there is a blacker Calumny behind, which he throws upon the whole body of Christians; as if they had corrupted the holy Scriptures to make them speak in favour of their Doctrines of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and of the <hi>Godhead of our Saviour.</hi> He says, in pursuance of this design, they added and left out as themselves pleased: and if their Divisions among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves had not hindred, they would not have left us any remain of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Christianity. This is indeed <hi>calumniating stoutly;</hi> but <hi>the dirt will not easily stick</hi> with sober and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men. For of what Scripture doth he say this? The Writings of the Old Testament, those were always in the hands of the Jews, and are so still; so that they can't be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Christians. For the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the New Testament, it is no less ridiculous to accuse the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of corrupting them in favour of these Doctrines. For if their Divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as he saith, have hindered them from doing this since the times of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:97513:73"/>the Christian Emperors, then the same have hindred them always; for there have been always divisions among Christians, enough to make them watch one another, and to hinder them from joyning together in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting of the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. N.</hi> may truly say, that the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Party did in the second and third Centuries complain of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence of the Hereticks in falsify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the sacred Books: and it is to the party of those, whom we call Orthodox Christians, that we owe the preservation of these Books, and the restitution of their Authority, which was so vigorously attack'd by most of the Hereticks. If <hi>M. N.</hi> will take advantage of some various read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that are in the several old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuscripts, or antient Versions, let him fall on as soon as he pleases; let him exercise his Criticks upon these Texts, and he shall soon have an answer.</p>
               <p>I cannot say that <hi>M. N.</hi> had a design to gratifie the Deist in this;
<pb facs="tcp:97513:73"/>though in many things he writes as if they had imployed him. But in this accusation which he repeats so often, and in such virulent Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, he sheweth plainly a design to make the Clergy odious, and bring them under suspicion of having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to destroy the holy Scriptures, and to change the Christian Religion. For this we must leave him to the Justice of God, who seeth the Hearts, and will render to every Man accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Works.</p>
               <p>I might easily have justified the authorities which Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> hath quoted to prove that the Doctrine of the Divinity of Christ was brought down by Succession from the Apostles till <hi>Justin Martyr</hi>'s time; and it would have been easie enough, after the light that I have given into <hi>M. N</hi>'s System, to have shewed the vanity of his Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections against them. But I thought that would have engaged me into too great a length. And since Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> is still alive, and possibly may not think fit to let him escape with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:97513:74"/>some Animadversion, I thought it not so proper to take the business out of his hands; especially since the Doctor hath laid in matter enough for it in those very Books that are written against by this Author.</p>
               <p>To conclude; As it was wholly in obedience to your Commands that I composed this small Treatise, so I leave it entirely at your disposal, to do with it accordingly as your great Wisdom shall think fit, to which I shall ever pay an absolute Submission. I am with the most profound re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:97513:74"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>